Heat. Heat.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Heat. Heat.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Good evening. Good day everybody and
welcome back to the Ask Abijit show.
Today we discuss history, Indian history
and world history. I have chosen a
number of questions that you have asked
in the comments and I'm going to take
those today. But before we do that as
always, let me see who all is there in
the live chat. I can see Mac 4 Amya Chri
has become a new member. Thank you very
much Amy Chri welcome to the membership.
I really appreciate that. Sai Suraj nine
real Vladimir Putin AJ Raul uh
geopolitical Dubai is here from Indor
good evening Chatanya Manuja is here.
Vorto anonymous artististic is here.
Good to see you. Uh seek for seeking
Chetanya Manuja once again. Sudhir Kumar
the Ashwini Dak 1894.
Uh I might testic again. Sar. All right.
S VSVS 2400. Namaste. Namaste. Good to
see you. Thank you so much. Uh Nawad
Tadas Namaste. VSVS once again. Uh Aush
Singh is here from Pranam Sarji. Good to
see you. Abhai Singh. Chetanya manuja
once again. Geopolitical way from Indor.
Um
who else do we have? Uh Swami is here.
Son J4s is also here. Vinina Jooshi.
Shashank Koshik. Good evening. Pratarana
Namaste sir Mahita Bushetti J Krishna
ma'am online yo bro good to see you
Shukla is here Adashini once again
Vikash PJ J desai hello civilian wizard
prrenam
um who else do we have Vikas PJ Shubam
Vare Sagar Gare
uh Sager Dadani Pray Paul from Kolkata
good to see you good to see you. Welcome
back. Kalist Mahushi says Haruhar
Mahadev. Yes indeed. Harar Mahadev. Uh
Shubam Shubam XJ Priyanka Javalia. Good
evening ma'am. Sager Dadani.
Uh who else? Nirvana Shang Shanks Kodi
Shiva good to see you Mr. Sumit.
Namaste.
Um who else do we have? Amish Mishra is
here. Good to see you. Sumit Sumit
Agarwal.
Have I watched Durand yet? I did watch
it. Yes, I will speak about it. Maybe
not today but maybe tomorrow. Yeah. Um
and uh Gajapati Dave is also here on the
live chat and everyone else. Okay. So
Bala Subraman good evening Ritik Tagi
namaste.
All right let's let's get going with the
questions. What questions do we have? As
always today is going to be history.
We're going to discuss various aspects
of history. So what's the first history
question for today? Here is the first
one. Amish Mishra says how rich was the
sunnath temple in the 11th century
before it was plundered and destroyed by
Mahmud of Gazni. The loot of sunnath
gave Mahmud of Gazni a worldwide fame.
He sent incalculable values of looted
gold and silver to the khif in Baghdad I
suppose and I'm sure he must have kept
huge lots with himself too. So how rich
was the subnath temple? So first of all,
where is the SNAT temple located? Let's
orient ourselves first of all. So let us
go to the map and put the map on the
screen and let's uh find the let's
locate
the place. So we're talking about
western India. We're talking about uh
the southern part of Sarashtra.
And here we have Sumnad, right? Uh the
town is called Viral. And there is a
temple, the great temple there. It's
it's it's the reconstructed
temple that we have uh over here.
Can we find it on the Google on the on
the map? Okay, here it is. Here it is.
So, this is the temple. This is the
modern reconstruction of the temple. And
this is the site where the ancient
temples stood. And the temple was
destroyed multiple times. First by
Mahmudi and then by various Dar Sultans.
and eventually by Aurange the Turk uh
king who the the tyrant who ruled India
in the uh six 17th and 18th century. So
this is the location it's in western
India the southern part of Saashtra.
Okay. Uh just for orientation now the
question is how rich was it? because we
have all these uh you know these stories
these records from the past that say
that Mahmud took so much incalculable
amount of wealth.
So Mahmud of Gazni
he uh
looted plundered and destroyed the
temple in the 11th century probably 1026
AD. At that time Gujarat was ruled by
the Solanki or or Chaolukia dynasty. The
king was Bhimadev Solanki. Okay. Rajput.
Today they are considered they they're
classified as Rajputs this dynasty. Wow.
And and there are records of the of the
temple by Persian chroniclers
who have uh described the temple as as
some as a temple that possessed
tremendous amounts a tremendous amount
of wealth in gold, silver, pearls,
jewels and this wealth was accumulated
over centuries maybe millennia
and they said that it was one of
probably one of the richest temples in
the whole of India. But there is no
there is no inventory that they've given
in in terms of the exact quantity of
let's say gold in terms of kilos or gold
in terms of there was this older uh unit
that was used mana. So they haven't
provided any of that. There was this uh
historian called
who said that no treasury of any king in
the world contained this much wealth. So
that's how much wealth was contained was
was there stored in the temple. Now the
question is why would a temple store so
much wealth today people won't
understand that right? See temples first
of all subnat is is one of the iconic
great temples. It's uh probably
this location where the current temple
stands. It's probably been the site of a
temple for thousands of years.
It is recorded that Lord Krishna when he
ruled over Duara this region he also
visited the place and his resting place
I mean not resting place but uh the
place where Lord Krishna died eventually
by after being shot by the arrow of a
hunter that temple is also in in Viral
nearby you can see it on the map
so it's a very ancient temple and
temples were places obviously holy
places this is a great jot linga temple
of Lord Shiva
And uh as such because it was it was
such a great temple people would you
know pilgrims would come from all over
the let's say Indosphere you know and
they would come and they would donate
whatever they could for the upkeep of
the temple and typically they would
donate more than was what was required
and so over the centuries and millennia
tremendous amounts of wealth I mean you
know you know uh treasure was
accumulated in the temple kings would
come from various parts of India. There
were times when India was under a single
emperor. There were times when when
India was was politically divided but
the kings would come on pilgrimages and
and donate large amounts of wealth and
that's how over time the temple
accumulated tremendous wealth and there
are some temples today in especially in
southern India where you know you have
large amounts of wealth. One of the
temples that has not been plundered
fortunately is the Sharipan Narabas
Swami temple in Kerala and that is known
to uh have a treasury that commands that
that contains a tremendous amount of
wealth. So that's how this sunnah temple
accumulated so much wealth. It's it's a
very ancient place and uh so what Mahmud
of Ghazni did is he came to the temple.
He was able to defeat the forces of
Bhimdev Soleni and he desecrated the
temple, killed all the brahmans, all the
priests, all the all the staff uh
beheaded them in the most merciless ways
and he you know damaged the temple as
far as possible. He destroyed the great
jotir linga the floating jotir linga
that was magnetically magnetically
levitated over there and he took away
all the wealth. Now um if you look at
Wikipedia, Wikipedia will quote Roila
Tapar okay and it will say that uh
according to Romeil Tapar about uh I
don't know 20 million dinars or
something worth of wealth was taken
away. I'm not sure how Romeila Tapar G
came up with this figure but she says 20
million dinars was taken away. That
that's the quantification of the wealth.
Now once again that's kind of vague
because what exactly is a dinar in
today's monetary terms is a dinar equal
to a certain amount of gold or is it
equal to something else? We are not
quite sure but Romela Tapper says 20
million dinars. Um the the truth and and
you have all kinds of popular articles
and social media posts etc. Sometimes
secondary literature not primary
literature but secondary sources that
state that maybe Mahmud took away a
treasure worth about a 100 million
dinars. Once again we don't know what is
the actual value of the dinar of that
time right?
So um we can't really trace the exact
quantity you know of of wealth uh
administrative records from that time
from the 11th century do not survive
[snorts] uh accounts detailed accounts
by Indians of the SNA temple of that
time from the 11th century do not
survive and that's why we can't really
put a precise number whether it is in
dinars whether it is in rupees whether
it is in kilos of gold dollars whatever
we can't really put a precise figure on
the amount of wealth that this uh great
temple contained. U but it is known to
have uh
you know made Mahmud a very wealthy man
and he was able to use that wealth to
finance his subsequent military
operations and uh you know yeah it made
him one of the wealthiest men in the
world and you had temples like this all
across India. I mean Zumnat may have had
more wealth than most temples but you
had temples that contained such wealth
all across the length and breadth of
India and all of that was plundered. So
you can imagine how rich India was
before the Turk invasions um began and
after the Turks it was the British that
plundered India and that's where that's
how we have ended up where we are today
and still and yet we have some temples
like the Shirat Munab Swami temple that
still contain trillions of dollars worth
of today's wealth. I mean if you were to
quantify that it's in the trillions of
dollars. Uh so yeah that is the deal
about the surah temple how rich it was
we can't really tell because we don't
have any contemporary records from that
time. Okay.
Math and CLFMAO says, "What's the lore
with the Nanda DVP?
Is there really a lost nuclear device
there?" I remember I had taken this
question several years ago, maybe 3
years ago or something. But let's
revisit this because these days it's
it's again in the news apparently.
So
it seems that there is a lost nuclear
device on the Nanda Dvi peak. First of
all, let's understand one thing. It's
not a nuclear weapon that was lost. It's
a nuclear device that contained a
specific isotope of plutonium. Not the
isotope that is used in uh nuclear
weapons, but it's plutonium 238 that was
uh contained in this device. Now, first
of all, let's locate the Nanda Dvi peak,
shall we? Let's do that.
So all we have to do is we have to go
north north northern part of India
Uttarakhand and you will see that there
is something called the Nanda Dvi
National Park over here. Okay. And if we
zoom in further we have mountains like
Trishul
and so on. And where is the Nanda Dvi
peak? Okay here it is. It is uh the
second highest peak in India after the
Kjanjunga if I am not mistaken. uh you
can check out the actual details but
here it is. This is the Nanda Dvi peak
the second highest mountain
within uh the present day boundaries of
India. This is the peak. All right.
Nanda Dvi. Now let us uh zoom out and
and and look at the surrounding region
especially north of Nanda Dvi. North of
Dunda Dvi you have Chinese occupied
Tibet
and further north you have Chinese
occupied Shinjang.
Now in Shinjang
present day China there is a place
called Lnor which is where the Chinese
in the 20th century tested their nuclear
weapons. Where is Ln? Let's let's figure
it out. Ln.
Let's find it. It'll zoom in quickly.
Okay, this is Ln. It's it's essentially
barren land obviously that's where you
will test nuclear devices not in a
populated area so we can see how far it
is from Nanda Dvi about 1500 km or so
let's let's uh take a rough rough
estimate shall we from here let's
measure the distance to Lnor
yeah about 1500 roughly kilometers
pretty far away right from Nanda Dvi so
the so in 1960 what 64 the Chinese
tested their first nuclear
device in in Lnor in Chinese occupied
Shinjang and that was a matter of
concern for the United States. Okay.
And at that time I I when did when did
the great Mr. Nehu die India's greatest
ever
see Shri Javaharlal Nehuji was India's
greatest ever prime minister and it was
a tragic day for India when Shri Neuji
passed away I think it was in 1963 or 64
probably 1964 so a tremendous tragedy
for India Shri Neuji passed away and
subsequent to his passing Mr. Shastri
Mr. Albadu Shastri became India's prime
minister and he passed away in early
1966.
Okay. So it's in 1964 that the Chinese
test their first nuclear device nuclear
weapon in Lnor and the Americans are
concerned. India also I suppose may have
possibly been concerned. I mean Mr. Nu
we could not I mean you know he was so
great we could not understand him but uh
may he he may have been concerned. So
the Americans said to India, let's uh
set up a you know a signals intelligence
station in northern India on the Nanda
peak or near the peak of the great
mountain from which we can look far into
China. We can see the Nanda mountain is
about roughly 8 km tall, 8 km high and
from that vantage position you can look
far into China into Chinese occupied
territory. Okay. So that was the deal.
So the Americans proposed that they
would uh furnish a device. They would
come with a device uh which would uh be
a signals intelligence device and they
will place it on the Nanda Dvi peak or
near very close to the peak and from
there the device would acquire signals
intelligence essentially
uh you know yeah data about Chinese
activities what the Chinese were doing.
So what kind of device was this is the
question. So this this expedition
happened in 1965
in in probably October or something 1965
which is a strange time to do such an
expedition. October it's autumn right?
October November is autumn and the
weather isn't great in October November
in the Himalayas. The best time to do it
do something like this is during
springtime or summertime when there is
less snow it's it's warmer in autumn
it's going to be cloudier and the you
know the weather will be rougher but
they decided to do it in October there
must have been some reasons for that so
the uh expedition was happened in
October 1965 and there was a team of
Americans maybe probably more than 10
Americans who came and they were
accompanied by Indian mountaineers and
you know officials of various kinds. Uh
and they climbed the mountain and they
they they had this uh
this RTG radioisotope thermmoelect
electric generator which contained
plutonium. It contained more than 50
kilog of plutonium. It was called the
snap 19c. Okay. So this so the equipment
was aboutif more than 50 kg of plutonium
plutonium 238 which is not the one that
is the isotop that's used in bombs and
it had the the equipment also contained
a 10- ft antenna.
So the uh the RTG radioiso
thermmoelectric generator would provide
the heat and the the power needed to
power the system and the antenna would
acquire signals from within Chinese
occupied territory and monitor future
Chinese nuclear tests. Okay, that was a
deal.
So the expedition went ahead in October
1965 and while climbing the mountain
pretty high on the mountain there was an
extreme weather event a blizzard which
is a massive snowstorm
and it became um the weather became so
extreme that the expedition members had
no choice but to leave the expedition
behind somewhere on a ledge in the
mountain and go back down otherwise they
would have lost their lives. Right. So
they left the equipment behind on a
ledge on the mountain near the peak of
the mountain somewhere near the peak and
they tried their best to climb down the
mountain and fortunately for them they
all survived. No, nobody lost their life
and then the deal was that you know they
knew where they had kept the equipment
and when the weather would be better
they would go back and finish the
mission. So the weather, you know, after
October in the Himalayas, the weather
gets worse, not better. So you have to
wait out the entire winter. And then in
spring, that's what, March, April,
around that time, that's when you can uh
have sufficiently decent weather to
climb the mountain again. So that's what
they did. So they went back the next
spring, they climbed all the way up and
there's nothing there. Okay. So the
device is gone. And uh what happened is
the question. How did the device
disappear all the way up there on the
mountain? So there's two possibilities,
okay, two logical possibilities. One
possibility is that maybe there was a
blizzard again. Maybe there was an
avalanche. An avalanche is when there's
a, you know, hundreds of tons of snow
falling down the mountain. It's very
common in the Himalayas. So maybe there
was another law and that may have
dislodged the device and know the device
may have tumbled down into some travass
or something down the mountain slope and
maybe it still lies somewhere there
buried under I don't know how many
dozens of meters of snow perhaps. Okay,
that's one possibility of, you know, a
natural explanation, a Nava launch or
something that dislodged the device, the
plutonium uh RTG and the antenna and
that's how the device was lost and maybe
it tumbled all the way down. That's one
possibility. The second possibility is
also a logical possibility that the
Indian government sent mountaineers
during the winter or whenever and they
retrieved the device and maybe for
whatever reason. So that's two
possibilities. Those are the two logical
possibilities. Now which is true, we
don't know. But the device disappeared.
The device is lost.
Now in case the Indian government went
and retrieved the device and did
whatever tests, experiments, whatever
and maybe reverse engineered technology,
what whatever the reason is, in that
case we are fine. In that case there is
no danger. But if there was a launch and
the device actually tumbled down the
mountain and it maybe lies somewhere in
the catchment plane of the Ganga, then
it's a very big danger. Now let me
explain why. So once again we go back to
the map and understand why this region
is so sensitive and critical. So this
region the Nanda Dvi National Park
region where you have the great mountain
where once again I'm going to have to
locate it. Where is the where's the
mountain? Nanda Dvi.
Ah come on man.
Nanda Dvi
uh Chamol Utrahan. Okay here it is.
Nanda Dvi Parvat here is the mountain.
So this region that we are talking about
it is the catchment area for the Ganga.
Okay.
The catchment region from where the
great Ganga river the Ganges like they
say in English the Ganga the Ganga gets
its waters from this region. So what
happens is that this is the Himalayas
right? As you can see it's it's the
heart of the Himalayas. You got all
these peaks with glaciers and snow and
ice. And when the ice and snows melt
those all of that water trickles down
into a couple of rivers over here, the
Alaknandanda River and the Bhagati
River. Where is Dva Praag? Let us let us
find where is Dva Praag. Okay, let me
just search for it. Da pra.
[snorts]
Okay. It is over here. So it is over
here that you have two of these rivers
the bhagati and and the alaknanda that
that merge and they see over here it
says the bhagirati right this one here
and over here it says the alaknandanda.
But once they merge what is it called?
The Ganga. So it is at dva pra that the
Ganga actually emerges out of the merger
of the Alakanda and the Bagrati and the
catchment region for those rivers is the
Nanda Dvi you know region.
So if there is a device that contains
plutonium
which is lying over there exposed to the
elements maybe the the walls of the
device are corroding maybe there is you
know natural grinding because of because
of either the wind or rocks or whatever.
In that case the plutonium may actually
spill out
and then it may get dispersed. It see
when plutonium spills out you have
plutonium oxide particles that are you
know dispersed in the region and when
snows and ice melt and all that mixes
with water it becomes part of the
sediment
the sediment and and and the sediment
that is floating in the river okay in in
the water and if that ends up in the
aland the bhagati and eventually into
into the Ganga that can poison hundreds
of millions of people who live
downstream
Right? Because the Ganga goes all the
way down from Uttar Pradesh all the way
into West Bengal eventually to into
Bangladesh where it is called the Padma
river. Now why is this dangerous? If the
plutonium you know it spills out what
happens? So if the if the capsule
ruptures
then the plutonium is exposed to the
elements it forms plutonium oxide. Those
particles eventually you know merge you
know they flow out uh into the air. They
mix with the snows, the ice, they
eventually melt. The ice and snow
eventually melts, goes into the river.
Now plutonium is an extremely toxic
substance. There are multiple isotopes
of plutonium. Plutonium 238, plutonium
239, there is 240, 241. The plutonium
isotope that is used in nuclear weapons
is plutonium 239. Okay, it's the more
common isotope. So plutonium is not a
naturally occurring element. It's a
man-made element. It's a heavy metal.
It's a man-made heavy metal and it is
produced in nuclear reactors.
So plutonium 239 which is used in
nuclear weapons, it has a halflife of
about 24,000 years. Which means that if
you have 1 kilo of plutonium 239,
then in 24,000 years about half of it
will decay.
But the plutonium that is used in the in
this uh in this device that was lost, it
was not plutonium 239. It was it was
plutonium 238. And plutonium 238 has a
half life of 88 years. Which means if
you have 1 kilogram of plutonium 238,
half of it will decay in 88 years. If
you had 50 kg like we had in the device,
then about 25 kg will decay and no
longer be a problem in 88 years. And
then the rest of the plutonium, 25
kilos, half of it will decay in another
88 years and another half and so on.
That's how it goes. That's that's the
concept of halflife of radioactive
elements in nuclear physics. Now
plutonium is also extremely toxic. See
why was plutonium 238 it used? because
it is it it it uh it is a heat
generator. Okay, it generates heat and
uh it can also be used for for keeping
uh your equipment your circuits warm in
the extremely cold temperatures up there
and also it can it can produce power. It
uh gives off alpha radiation which is
essentially helium nuclei.
Now how does plutonium affect human
beings?
It will cause radiation poisoning. The
most dangerous form of plutonium
poisoning is when you inhale plutonium
particles maybe plutonium oxide
particles that will be very easily
absorbed by the body and it will get
absorbed in your tissue in your bones
and whoever is is unfortunately you know
uh who has got this they're going to get
cancer. It's almost a guarantee.
Now if you absorb plutonium oxide
through water then it is it has a lower
probability of getting absorbed in your
gut in your digestive tract but it it
still obviously emits alpha particles
and it can you know still give you
cancer. So uh [clears throat]
that's the situation. So plutonium is
extremely toxic. If someone is exposed
to plutonium they're going to almost
guarantee to get get cancer. um if it is
plutonium oxide that's out in the
atmosphere or in water but if it is
sealed within within a radioiso through
the that generator RTG in that case it
is not going to be that much of a
problem. So that is the situation. So
that is the story and
and I think in 1978
uh the Indian Atomic Energy Commission
had conducted some kind of testing in
the rivers in the region and they found
no evidence of plutonium being present
and I suspect that the government of
India must be testing from time to time
in case it has actually been lost
otherwise it may be performative testing
or or whatever. So the best case
scenario for us is that the government
of India
it retrieved
the plutonium in 1965 or 66 winter
around that time before the Americans
came back. That's the best case
scenario. The worst case scenario is
that the thing was lost and after all
these years maybe it will well I hope it
doesn't happen but if it ruptures it's
going to be a big catastrophe for
millions hundreds of millions of people.
So that is that is the thing that is the
story about the Nanda Dvi plutonium
device that was supposedly lost there
and yeah it could pose a real danger to
people. Okay next question.
Okay Omega Omega [snorts] Realms says as
someone who is not Indian or Hindu how
are the Greekans and later Indo- Greeks
viewed in India today? Are they viewed
neutrally as a distant culture that no
longer exists? Are they viewed
positively as people who brought
positive things to India? Or are they
viewed more negatively as conquerors or
colonizers who tried to replace India's
culture? Well, the truth is that most
Indians are today not even aware of
them. The most ind that an Indian person
will know about the Indo Greeks is maybe
a paragraph somewhere in a history
textbook and you know maybe in high
school or something
unless you actually study history at a
at a higher level maybe as part of a
bachelor's degree or or uh master's
degree or a PhD level in that case you
may perhaps uh study this in more
detail. So most Indians do not even know
about uh the the Indo- Greeks. Most
Indians I would assume don't even know
about them. And [clears throat]
obviously there is this you know in
popular culture everyone kind of knows
about Alexander. Most Indians believe
that Alexander invaded India and
successfully defeated King Porus who was
a great king of the time and then
decided to go back or whatever. That's
what most Indians believe. The truth is
that something entirely different
happened. It was a catastrophe, a
disaster for Alexander and his attempt
to invade India killed him. Ended ended
up killing him and then he u the
governors he left behind
they then established these you know um
these city states kind of you know small
kingdoms in the northwest of India
present day Gandhar, Afghanistan etc.
present day parts of Pakistan and parts
of Punjab as well, right? And those
eventually became the the Indo- Greek uh
kingdoms.
You could also call them Dracoactrian or
whatever. And that's what happened. Now,
most Indians don't know about this. Most
most Indians have no awareness of this.
Uh most Indians know about Alexander.
Most Indians think of Alexander as this
great heroic figure. And there have been
movies made about Alexander in in India
that typically depict him in a very
positive light. So most Indians kind of
think of Alexander as a great conquering
hero and not a bad person overall,
someone who potentially brought
something good to India. Most Indians
would probably think of it that way. Uh
are the Indogreeks viewed negatively as
conquerors or colonizers? No.
Most Indians don't think don't know
about them. those who know about them
most of them don't think of Indo- Greeks
as as you know in in a negative light as
colonizers because they weren't
colonizers they Alexander did try to
invade India didn't did not work he left
behind these governors and the governors
eventually the Indo Greeks they
eventually assimilated into the
population of India today lots of people
in northern western India will have a
fractional amount of maybe 1% 2% Greek
ancestry nobody will know nobody will
care so that's how is they and the truth
is that the Greeks never tried to
replace Indian culture. They did not do
that. They brought their own culture
with them. Okay? They set set up
kingdoms, small kingdoms in the
northwest part of India and they did not
ever try to impose Greek culture, Greek
customs on the local populations and
they eventually themselves Indianized.
So um the so there is no question of of
uh regarding them negatively as
colonizers who tried to replace India's
culture because they did not try to do
that. U eventually what happened was
that you had this new kind of uh
artistic styles that emerged out of
Gandhara you know the Gandhara style art
style the Indo- Greek art style which
blended Indian styles with Greek styles.
So as you can see it was a syncret it
was a syncratic kind of culture that
evolved and existed for a while a few
centuries and then eventually even that
disappeared and become part of became
part of the overall greater Indian
culture. So that's that's how it went
and most Indians either are not aware of
the Indo Greeks or regard them as either
either as in a neutral way or in a
positive way. I would imagine that very
few Indians, a very small minority of
Indians may regard the Greeks, the Indo-
Greeks in a negative light.
And when it comes to present day
Pakistan etc., I think they call what
they call Alexander Sikundar and they
they kind of regard him as some kind of
hero, some kind of a good person.
And there are some small ethnic groups
up in the Himalayas
who are regarded as being descendants of
Alexander soldiers. For example, the
Kalash people. Um the the the the people
who are part of what is now called
Nuristan which was originally called
Kafiran because they held on to Hinduism
until the 19th century.
Uh even the Kalash people. Do you would
you like to see what the Kalash people
look like? Okay, let's not this, not the
map. We'll uh ask our friend Google.
Okay, so here we have it. Kalash people.
So the Kalash people are this small
ethnic group in present day the Chhatral
region especially of Pakistan who look
kind of European. I mean you can see you
know many of them have blonde hair uh
light color skin uh blue eyes and uh
they have features that some people
would regard as European features right
um and these people are erroneously
considered to be descendants of the uh
uh soldiers of Alexander they actually
aren't they are a very interesting
ethnic group which u a very old ancient
ethnic group they have been kind of
isolated in the mountains for millennia
Yeah. And their genetics are actually
Indian, not Greek. But you know, so
there are all these legends and myths
that have sprung around, sprung up
around the Indo- Greek period. So
overall, the answer is that nobody
almost nobody in India regards the Indo
Greeks negatively. It's either neutral
or positive.
Rohan Biri says, why was Ian so
terrible? Ian the terrible. Yes.
Um there are I mean he is regarded as
one of the most terrifying kings that
Russia ever had. So first of all Ivan
the terrible he lived in the 16th
century. Okay in the middle of the 16th
century. Now he was the first Russian
king to call himself a tsar.
Before him Russian kings were called
grand princes.
But Ian the terrible called himself the
the Tar and that's how this this title
of Tar took root took root in Russia and
then you had a lineage of Tarinas.
So what does Sar mean? Sar is the
Russian form of Caesar Kaiser. Yeah. So
Ivan the terrible he was called Grojni.
Grojni in Russian and Grosni kind of
means terrible. It also means awesome.
Oh inspiring. um that sort of thing,
formidable, scary. So, it kind of means
that that's what the word grosi means in
Russian. Uh it doesn't necessarily mean
cruel. It means uh scary, frightening,
all inspiring, uh formidable, that sort
of thing. Now, why is Ian called Ivan
the terrible? Like I said, he lived in
the 16th century, 1530 to he lived for
what 55 or so years, 54, 55 years, and
then he died.
So let's go back to the beginnings of
Ivan the Terrible. When he was a small
child, his dad died, his father died.
His father died when he was about 3
years old. And 5 years later, when Ivan
was about 8 years old, his mother died.
And she was most likely poisoned by
various noble families who were
competing for power in Russia. Okay?
And Ivan had this brother. I don't
remember his name, but he was deaf and
mute.
And Ivan and his little brother, they
were treated as political football by
the competing royal noble families in
Russia who wanted to be the power behind
the throne. And Ivan and his brother
were neglected terribly
when he was a child. They would be
dressed in rags and they would be
starving. They would not be given enough
food and they would be given very poor
clothes to wear. I mean almost almost
dressed in rags. So they were almost
like
street children. That's how they were
treated. Okay. Uh by these noble
families. There were two major noble
families in Russia at the time and they
were competing with each other and and
trying they were trying to be the power
behind the throne.
But Ivan survived his childhood and by
the by the time he was 13 he had
consolidated enough power to have one of
the princes of one of the noble families
executed during a feast. So during a
feast he he accused that that prince of
of mismanaging the rule of whatever
region he was ruling and he was then
executed in a very brutal way. Uh there
are all kinds of stories about the
execution. Maybe he was eaten by dogs or
something but most likely he was just
beaten to death by the jailers. So that
was uh [clears throat] the first
show of uh of of independence of Ivan
when he was 13 years old and he formally
became the Char of Russia when he was 16
years old and he married this young lady
whose name was what? What was I the
Terrible's wife's name? Alexandra was
it? Ian the Terrible
wife. Wife. Anastasia was it Anastasia?
Anastasia Romanova.
His first and most beloved wife. He he
had several wives like it says. Okay.
But his beloved wife was his first wife.
Anastas Anastasia Romanova. So once he
becomes a sar he ruled very nicely for a
while. Okay. He implemented reforms and
he had a nice happy loving stable
marriage and he was fine. But then but
because of his terrible childhood he had
this great distrust this great mistrust
of the nobility. He believed that they
were after him. They wanted to kill him.
Okay. So he always distrusted the
military the the the nobility the
nobility of his country. Then what
happens is that uh he led the conquest
of various parts of Russia. He he
expanded his empire. uh he went to the
the region of Kazan, Astrahan. So the
territories that belong to the Tatars is
the Tatars are Turk origin ethnic group
in Russia today and they the and they
were the the formidable enemies of the
Russians when the Russian Empire was
expanding because it was expanding into
Tatar territory,
descendants of the Hoons. Yeah. Turks.
So uh so Ian conquered Kazan, he
conquered Astrahan down south Crimea
region. He expanded his territory. He
expanded his empire and he started
slowly gaining this reputation as a
warrior a victorious
fearsome warrior king. Okay. And uh
that's how this this image starts you
know starts forming that Ivan is gni
Ivan is terrible. Then he was fighting a
war, the the so-called Levonian war with
Lithuania and one of his close allies
who was again a noble, he deflected to
the other side to to the Lithuanian side
and he took command of a Lithuanian army
and defeated the Russians.
So that once again reminded Ivan that
you know what uh the kind of childhood
he had and the nobles were always
plotting and conspiring against him and
so this this reinforced his mistrust of
the nobles. So what Ivan did is that he
abdicated the throne. He said I don't
want to rule. And he gave up his throne
and he gave the power to the boy which
is a group of nobles and clergy you know
church people priests. So he left
Moscow. He went to a neighboring city
which is you know not very far away but
not close also and he left the boy to
rule Russia and it was almost
impossible. They found it almost
impossible to rule the country. It was
really really difficult. they could not
make the decisions and then this they
they had to go to him and beg him to
take the throne back.
So he said okay I'll take the throne
back on one condition you let me rule
whichever way I want to rule and whoever
I consider to be traitors of the enemies
of the nation you let me deal with them
in whatever way I want. So they gave him
this right this permission. Okay. And
that's when
that's when he divides the country into
two group into two territories. One was
a territory which was which would be
administered by the nobility and the
other territory would be administered
only by him. It was called the
Opricnina.
Okay.
So he created the Opricina
and he created a secret police called
the Opritniki. They were they would be
dressed in black. They would have they
had some connection with the church and
they reported only to him. They were
loyal to him. And he used the Opricniki,
the secret police to unleash a reign of
terror in this region called the Opric
Nina. and he went after any and every
person he considered to be a traitor or
to be disloyal to him. So the secret
police it tortured and killed thousands
maybe tens of thousands of people. Okay.
It was a kind of a terror apparatus. It
was like the like like the gestapo you
could say. Yeah. And uh they
they they
took the land of people who were
considered to be traitors who were
suspected of being traitors, suspected
of being destroy disloyal and those
people in their families would be killed
off in the most horrific of ways. Okay,
torture was common. People would be
burned alive and
let's not go into the details. So it was
just absolute terror. Okay. Um so that's
in the 1560s and then there was this
city north [snorts] west of Moscow near
St. Petersburg. It is called Nogurod.
Okay. It was the second largest city in
Russia and it was considered to be a
rival of Moscow and Peter was deeply
suspicious of the people of Nogarod. He
believed that they were not loyal to
him. They were traitors. So he attacked
Nogorod, besieged the city, conquered
it, sacked it and there were mass
executions, horrific atrocities, 10 to
15,000 people were killed off. Okay. Uh
monasteries were destroyed, churches
were destroyed, priests and you know
monks were killed, merchants were
killed, politicians and nobles were
killed. Essentially it was merciless
cruelty and he essentially destroyed the
city of Ngurod. It did not recover for
centuries you know uh because of what he
did. So that reinforced his reputation
of being a very vicious cruel ruler and
he he started descending into this
mental instability after his wife died.
So he was very fond of his first wife
Anastasia Romanova. Okay. And after she
died that that stabilizing and
moderating influence in his life was
gone. And then he married multiple
ladies. Some he married for like less
than a year or whatever. Uh I think six
or eight I don't know what the actual
number is but a large number of ladies
he married. But he became mentally
unstable. He became deeply deeply
paranoid and he went on this long
decadesl long rampage against anybody
who considered who he considered to be
disloyal. Eventually, you see, he
created this this uh police secret
service force, right, called the Opric
Niki. Eventually, he started suspecting
that the Oprici were were potentially
plotting against him. So, he disbanded
disbanded the Opric Nikki and had many
of them also executed. Okay. So,
[snorts] that's how it was. That's how
he was super paranoid. And near the end
of his life when he was probably in his
what early 50s around 50 um he had a
couple of sons maybe more than a couple
of sons at least two sons he had and one
of his sons who was who was the crown
prince he was married his wife was
pregnant and in the palace uh Ivan
happened to meet his son's wife and
apparently she was not dressed properly
enough or something she was heavily
pregnant and he beat her up. He beat her
so badly that she miscarried. So his
son, the crown prince come, crown prince
came and confronted his father. How dare
you do this to my wife to your own
daughter-in-law? And Ivan, he was
carrying some kind of staff. He hit his
son on the head with a staff and that
ended up killing his son. So he had his
daughter-in-law miscarry his own
grandchild and then he killed his own
son.
And there is this extremely uh famous
painting of Ivan.
[clears throat]
Let's see that.
Ian the terrible and his son, right?
Um ah safe search. Yeah, because it is
not a nice image to see. So there we
have it. You can if you want you can
look into it in greater detail. This is
when he realizes what he has done to his
son. So he was just mentally unstable at
this point in life and he died in his
what in his mid-50s or something.
So that was a deal about Ivan. He
started off as a reasonably good king.
As long as he was married to his first
life, he was fine. He ruled well. He had
a terrible childhood. In his childhood,
because he was so powerless, it is said
that he would torture animals, throw
dogs and cats off the roof and pluck the
feathers of birds, that sort of thing.
So because of his extremely traumatic
childhood, he he became cruel. He was
fine as long as his wife was alive. But
afterwards, after she died and possibly
she was also poisoned. His mother was
poisoned, his wife was also poisoned.
There were exumations of those of the of
the bodies of his mother and wife in the
20th or 21st centuries wherever and
poison was most likely detected in the
bones. So his mother was poisoned, his
eventually his wife was also poisoned.
He became extremely paranoid and he went
after anybody he suspected was disloyal
or a traitor. He had lots and tens of
thousands of people tortured, killed in
terrible ways and what he did to his own
family was also brutal. So that's why he
is called Ivan the terrible.
[clears throat]
Hope that explains this.
Nirvana Shanks says, "As I've grown
older, I've become in increasingly
disillusioned with the idea of
democracy. I'm not even sure if this is
a history question or geopolitics
question." Well, history and geopolitics
are interconnected. So, we can take
this. [clears throat]
But I genuinely no longer understand
what democracy actually is. Is it simply
elections or is it something deeper like
civil liberties, rule of law,
institutional checks, individual rights?
What where exactly is the line beyond
which a system stops being a democracy?
What is true democracy supposed to be?
And even if it if such a form exists in
theory, is it really the best model of
governance for a large and complex
civilization? Right? Democracy.
Well, democracy
for the past century or so,
most people believe that democracy is
all about holding elections. So once in
five years or in the case of the US,
four years, but most of the world, it's
five years. Once in 5 years there's an
election and that makes your country a
democracy and as part of this this
process you have to go and vote. So your
job as a citizen is to vote once in 5
years and then leave the rest to the pe
to the individuals who are elected.
That's how it is. Now ideally democracy
is not supposed to be like that. Ideally
democracy is supposed to be more
participative.
For example, let's say you you have a
football club and you appoint a manager
of the football club. Let's say you have
a cricket cricket team. Okay, let's say
you have a cricket team, national
cricket team and you have appointed a
coach, a manager of the cricket team.
Let's say you give him a maybe
three-year contract. Hypothetical,
completely hypothetical.
Now if he doesn't perform
well
and you lose multiple you know series
very quickly then you have the right to
sack him to fire him after 3 months
after 6 months whenever required. You
don't have to honor the old the entire
three three-ear contract right. So if
you are running a football club, a
cricket team, you can hire a manager or
coach for a certain number of time, but
you can fire the person if the person
doesn't doesn't perform, if the
performance is not satisfactory.
Right? If you hire a CEO,
if you appoint a CEO of a company, you
let's say you are on the board of a
company and the board appoints a certain
person as a CEO, you give that person
let's say two year, three year tenure
initially contract. Okay. But if the
quarterly returns aren't good, if the if
the if the the quarterly returns are
shocking,
you can fire the person
after one quarter, after two quarters,
whatever. You don't have to honor the
entire contract. But in democracy,
once you elect a person
for 5 years, you're supposed to shut up
and get get lost and let the person do
whatever for 5 years. There's nothing
you can do about it, right? That's one
of the big issues with the democracy,
right? It's not it should not be like
that. It is possible that people may be
compromised. People promise one thing
and and deliver something else or don't
deliver anything at all. That happens. I
think it's pretty common in democracy.
Um, another issue with democracy is that
democracy can be game. The democratic
process, the electoral process can be
gamed. It can be hacked. There are
multiple ways of doing it. Vote bank
politics. Democracy is based on one
assumption. The basic central assumption
in democracy in electoral democracy is
that in an election each individual
will vote for a candidate based on what
they think is the best candidate. Merit.
It is assumed that each voter will vote
based on what they think is the merit of
the candidates. But in reality,
merit often has nothing to do with the
way people vote. They vote based on
religion. They b vote based on these
days cast in India. They vote based on
maybe they have been given some money.
Maybe they may been made some promises
that are bad for the country but good
for them.
There are vote banks that are created by
importing illegal administrators into a
country and settling them in a region in
a ward, municipal ward or whatever. So
the local people who are actually
citizens, their vote doesn't count
anymore because the the the
people who have been settled in a slum
or whatever, they're going to now
outvote them and they will vote for
whoever allows them regularizes their
their citizenship or whatever. So there
are so many ways of gaming and hacking
democracy. When it comes to social
media, it's so easy for foreign
countries to influence elections by by
gaming social media because they own the
social media platforms. So that's
another way of of hacking democracy and
making democracy completely into a joke
essentially, right? Then there are
nations where the
for example the European Union. Okay.
[snorts] Who rules the European Union?
It is the individuals who sit in
Brussels, the capital of the EU, right?
But those people are unelected.
So in a European Union nation, the
people will vote for their local
representatives in the in the nation's
assembly. they'll vote for their
president or prime minister or whatever.
But it is the EU government in Brussels
that actually rules these countries.
They determine the policies that will be
applicable on the on the people who have
never voted for them.
Economic policies, immigration policies,
dos and don'ts and whatnot.
So where's the democracy in this?
Where's the democracy? There's no
democracy. It's a joke.
Then you have some nations like Japan
for example.
No matter who you vote for, they can't
do a thing about the occupation, the
military occupation that the country is
under.
H
their constitution is written by
foreigners. That can't be changed. So
where's the democracy? Just having
elections is not democracy.
There are so many issues with democracy.
The the truth is that there is no real
true democracy in the world. Ideal
democracy,
idealized democracy where you actually
vote for representatives based on based
purely on their on their merit. That
doesn't happen anywhere in the world.
There are some countries where it's a
democracy in name because you only have
two political parties. Only two parties.
You can vote for either this one or that
one. And both political parties have the
same economic policies and the same
military policy and the same foreign
policy.
So where's the democracy again? So
democracy unfortunately is a big sham
that has been pulled over the people of
the world. And what they do to justify
it is that they will teach you in your
school, education, textbooks, etc. that
democracy is the best thing. Without
democation doesn't have democracy, it's
evil.
Right?
So uh nam what exactly is democracy?
Is it only elections? It's not
elections. Is it about civil liberties?
No. Not not necessarily civil civil
liberties. Rule of law, civil liberties,
institutional checks, individual rights,
all of these can be available to
citizens even in a non-democratic
arrangement.
Right?
So um democracy is not simply elections.
Democracy means you get to you get to
decide who represents you at c at a
certain level in the governance system
in the government.
So you can vote for your local municipal
bodies who's going to
who's going to be in in those m
municipal bodies. You can vote for your
state bodies like the legislative
assembly, MLAs. Then you can vote in
India for the central government, the
MPs, members of parliament. So there are
multiple levels of voting and multiple
levels of representation. But at the end
of the day, what does it give you?
Not sure what it gives you. Uh and it's
not just India, it's all over the world.
There are flaws everywhere. The system
can be gamed. Democracy can be hacked.
Democracy exists in many places only in
name. And that's a that's the problem.
So democracy has increasingly become
a sham in the world.
It is just a means of ruling people. I
mean
for example in New York
in New York in the 1930s4s50s
there was this gentleman called Robert
Moses
who ran the city
okay and it would be democratic elected
democratically elected etc.
And he said that he never did any
political dealings. He built everything
in New York, all the construction, all
the uh all the development activity
based on what people needed. But at the
but if you look behind the scenes and
you go below the surface, he
had all the politicians on his side.
So there is this sort of corruption
everywhere. It's not just in India. I
mean, Robert Moses is a great example of
someone who appears on the surface to be
such a great visionary developer,
somebody who transformed the city of New
York, who displaced
millions of people to create new
infrastructure in the city. But what he
did ended up being worse
for the poorest sections of sections of
society.
So you have this issue everywhere in the
world. So democracy is is increasingly a
sham now. It doesn't it it gives people
the illusion that they have control and
and they have power over the system.
Actually they have no power whatsoever.
So what is the what is the best model of
governance? Well, it depends on your
your history and your culture. And
historically the the form of governance
that has worked the best is monarchy.
Historically, that's the form of
governance that has worked the best. Do
what what with this information whatever
you want.
Amisha Mishra says, "What's the oldest
brick disc ever discovered? How did
early bricks differ? Are these bricks
still standing?"
Oldest bricks.
So, the oldest bricks discovered that
have been discovered archaeologically
are found in West Asia.
in Syria, in Turkey,
and in um
in Israel, well, the west bank of the
river Jordan where you have Palestinians
who live there. So, there is this place
called Tel Awad,
Black Tel in Syria. Okay, let's let's
look that up. Okay, Tel Awad.
Tel Asad. Okay, it's double L whatever.
So if you see Tel Awad first of all uh
let us go to the map and see where it is
located.
So Tel al-Assad.
Uh let's zoom out a little.
So as you can see it's in Syria,
northeast Syria.
And now let's zoom in and see what it
looks like. Do we see anything here?
Tell Alasad. As you can see it's some
ancient archaeological site clearly.
Right now let us now uh once again tell
us
and let's see some images and you will
see ancient bricks
here
ancient bricks
talasad.
Okay. So the thing is that they have
discovered really ancient bricks in this
uh in this site. Um
oh you can see some bricks here
maybe some here also. So this is one
such place it is in present day Syria
Telaswad. And the bricks that they have
discovered there about are about 7,500
from 7,500 BC. There is another place
called Jericho.
Jericho in the west bank.
West Bank. Okay. Over there also they've
discovered uh ancient bricks that are
about that from that time period maybe
7,000 BC or 7,500 BC. And then there is
one more called Catalyuk
Catalyuk which is in
Turkey
and over here also they have discovered
very ancient bricks. Okay. So you you
can look up these these sites.
So these are the oldest archaeologically
discovered bricks and they're about they
are from about 7,500 BC to about 7,000
BC which is about almost 9 9 and a half
thousand years before today. And the
bricks they've discovered there
are
made of clay
mixed with
dried grass or hay and the clay has not
been fired. It has not been baked. So it
is raw clay. It is raw mud mixed with uh
dried grass with hay and that's the kind
of bricks they have disco that have been
discovered in these places
Jericho and tell alasad
closer home for us uh bricks have also
been discovered in Mehergar Mher is in
Balojasthan Pakistan occupied territory
and the bricks that have been discovered
there are from about 6,000 500 BC maybe
a thousand years later after Telasawad
Jericho and
the bricks they that have been
discovered in Maher. So Megod was part
of the extended extended Saraswati Hindu
phase of our history and the bricks
they've discovered there are kind of
rectangular [snorts]
again not not fired not baked some of
them are described as cigar- shaped
so that is uh in the Indian subcontinent
in Mherar Balojasthan
and the thing is that in the Saraswati
Sindu region the Sapasindu region there
has been very little archaeological work
that's been done. Thousands of
archaeological sites uh remain
unexavated. Nobody has ever bothered to
excavate them. So if that is done, maybe
we'll find older bricks in the region.
But as of now, it is these three sites
in West Asia that
have
where we have where we have discovered
the oldest bricks. Some of the bricks
are still standing. I mean see when you
do excavations
you discover ancient buildings under
layers of soil. Okay. So they're not
freestanding today but once they once
the archaeologists go and dig and
discover something then they are able to
excavate these ancient structures
buildings and yeah once they're
excavated they kind of stand to some
extent.
Uh so yeah that's the deal about ancient
bricks.
Rishi says there's a theory that the
gate, a tribe that inhabited what are
now the modern nations of Bulgaria and
Romania in classical antiquity were
actually Jats or at least the ancestors
of modern Jats. Do you think this theory
could be true?
The gate the Masagate
the Masagate
defeated the Persian emperor Kru.
They had a queen called Omirish
who took his head off.
So what's the question? What's the deal
about the gate and the masagate?
Are they connected to India's juts?
Well that I will refer you to an article
by professor subashk.
Okay. Subashk
Uttarakuru
and the Juts. Is that what it's called?
Yeah. Utturu and the Juts.
So what does the article say? Professor
Subashak has been on my podcast multiple
times. Uh great scholar.
Uh not now. So the Saka. So let's go to
to the portion about the the gate and
the Masagate. So Herodotus the Greek
historian says that one of the Skian
tribes was the Masagate
Sanskrit Mahajat
and it was settled somewhere in the
great plains to the east of the Caspian
Sea.
Tommy geography 6102 says they're much
further south near Kashmir.
They were also simply called the gate or
in Sanskrit jut and tisagate tishut.
Uh the Frankish benedicting monk Rabanus
Mauus stated the masagate are in origin
from the tribe of the of the skithians
and are called masagate as in heavy maha
as in strong gate. Uh during Alexander's
campaign in western India there were
rebellions of the soians backrans and
the masagate. From this it may be
concluded that they were to the south of
the bactreans and thus situated squarely
in Punjab.
They were they are also seen as
neighbors of the ashwakas which is
apparently the early form of the name
avagana for the avans used by the Indian
astronomer vah vahir.
When Arabs entered Sind in the seventh
century, the Juts were the chief tribe
they met and they called them Zat or
Alzat, right? We have discussed that
last week. The Alz
shows that the Juts were spread all the
way from Cind to Afghanistan and beyond.
Shiva is called Jut and Mahajut in the
Mahabharat and the Shiva stora
indicating that he was a leading deity
of the Jut for the Jut people. How do we
know that the language of the Juts was
Aryan or Indoarian? The Juts form about
25% of the population of Hiad and Punjab
and they're also present in large
numbers in Uttar Pradesh, Rajasthan and
other states. If they were an intrusive
group from Central Asia with a different
language, they would have been able to
maintain their separate speech just as
large intrusive groups in Europe and
Asia have done over centuries.
The most famous jut of ancient history
like I said is queen Tomish Sanskrit
Tamri named after a daughter of Daksha.
She k she defeated and killed the
emperor Kurush Cyrus in 530 BC and
Hirous describes her great victory.
Okay. Um
yeah so in Europe the the the Kate were
considered similar or equivalent to the
thrians who not surprisingly worshiped
Dionius the Greek form of Shiva and the
goddess Bendis Artemis who is seen as
equivalent to Dura.
So that is you you can look up the
article it's called utturu and the jats
it's by professor subash kak and you can
read it in more detail in your own time.
So the deal is
the the Gate and the Masagate
were were skithian tribes. Skitheians
the stakas.
The sakas themselves were of Indian
origin just as the Kushans were.
And
the Masagate and the Gate eventually you
you see they they found their way into
India and they spoke in Indoarian
language otherwise they would have been
m able to maintain their their foreign
language because they were present in
such large numbers.
So that is the deal about the gate and
the juts. The connection is that the
gate and the juts are the same people.
All right.
Leru online says why most of the ancient
Vishnu temples located all across the
world are considered uh to be Buddhist
temples despite the deity having shanka
chakra gada or the traces of what they
once were. Okay.
Well, who considers Vishnu temples to be
Buddhist temples? First of all, let's
understand that
Vishnu has many incarnations, right?
And the last incarnation is considered
to be Goautam Buddha. You had Lord
Krishna, before that you had Lord Rama.
Before that, you had others. And the
last incarnation is considered to be L
Goautam Buddha. So if you have a Vishnu
temple, you can say that you know
Goautam Buddha was a reincarnation of
Vishnu. So it can also be considered to
be a Buddha temple if you want to. Now
when it comes to Southeast Asia
which is all the way from Burma,
Thailand, Cambodia, Vietnam, Laos, the
entire region,
it will also include Indonesia etc. But
this entire region was for like more
than 2,000 years a Hindu region. It it
became Indianized and Hinduized over
time because of the efforts of the great
people of Kolinga, the great merchants
of Kolinga.
So and and you had kings who built great
temples in the region, Hindu temples.
Many Shiva temples are there but many
Hindu temples are also there. For
example, the great temple of Ankorwat in
Cambodia.
The temple of Ankurvat is today
considered to be a Buddhist temple, but
it was originally a Hindu temple. Let's
see this,
right? It's called a Buddhist. Okay,
Hindu temple. So here it says Hindu
temple in Cambodia. Right? But if we go
back ah
if we say here it says Buddhist temple.
So here it says Buddhist temple. Once we
do the search it says Hindu temple. So
it's both.
And that's because Lord Vishnu is a
shared deity and Buddhism is not really
a separate religion despite what people
will keep claiming. It is an
offshoot of Hinduism.
It is nothing but one specific form of
Hinduism. It is one of the philosophical
ways of life or or philosophical paths
within the Dharmic umbrella just like
Janism and so on so so on so forth.
Now if you go to for example
Thailand you will see lots of statues of
Lord Vishnu all over the place and the
locals worship
these statues. They worship Lord Vishnu
through the statues without classifying
it as either Buddhist or Hindu. It's
just part of their culture. But it is
westerners and India's
India's compromised historians who
classify all this as Buddhist.
Right? Vishnu is originally a pre-B
Buddhist God, a Hindu god. Right?
Buddhism came later. Buddhism arose
about 2 and a half cent thousand years
before today. But for thousands of years
before that, there was no Buddhism. But
Lord Vishnu was woripped.
So
you know there is this
there is this movement to deny the Hindu
origins of everything in the world right
now.
And there are multiple reasons for that.
cultural civilizational reasons,
geopolitical reasons. Right? So, India's
historians deny this, India's teachers,
professors deny it, India's textbooks
deny it, and western academics deny it.
And that's how it goes. But the fact is
that Vishnu is a Hindu deity.
It is also he is also Lord Vishnu is
also a Buddhist deity because Lord
Buddha is considered to be an
incarnation or reincarnation of Vishnu.
So that is the thing and and I I'll tell
you this denial of the Hindu origins of
everything can be seen everywhere.
For example, the great emperor Kaneska,
one of our greatest emperors. Okay,
let's let's Google Kaneshka.
Kaneshka the great
the great Kaneska the great so if we go
into the Wikipedia page okay see it's
going to talk about kaneshka and
Buddhism the in Buddhist tradition
keshka is regarded as utmost importance
gold coin of kanka with Buddha once
again Buddha Shakamuni Buddha Buddha
Buddha Buddha Buddha Buddha everywhere
the truth is that less than 1% of
Kaneshka's coins are have Buddhist
iconography on them. The overwhelming
majority of Kaneska's coins are either
they either depict Hindu gods or
synratic gods like Hellenistic gods,
Apollo etc. But the majority depict
Hindu gods. Some depict Zoroastrinism,
Aurora Mazda, etc. Some depict some
Greek deities and about 1% or less
depict the Buddha. But see how much
importance Wikipedia is giving to
Kesan's Buddhist the Buddhist imagery on
Kesha's coins. So that's how history is
distorted.
Let's ask Google. Okay. Uh let's see
what percentage of
kanishkas
kaneskas
ah coins
have
Buddhist imagery
let's see what percentage well under 1%
like I said
Buddhist imagery appears on well under
1% of all known coins of Kaneshka and
yet when you see the Wikipedia article
it's all Buddhism Buddhism Buddhism
Buddhism see Ganesha and Buddhism
this is the problem this is how they
distort history
okay that's the deal so there is this
this this
campaign
this movement to deny the Hindu origins
of everything and we have to be aware of
it.
Okay.
Sassan lion says Ayatahi
had half Hindi half Persian origin. His
grandparent was Ahmed Hindi was born in
Lacnau. After that in the 18th century
his family migrated to Iran
Kmeni.
So
Kmeni came to power in Iran
as a consequence of the 1979
revolution that happened in Iran, the
Islamic revolution that ousted the
puppet sha of Iran and brought in the
the government that still exists today,
the government of the clerics, the
government of the ayatas, right? A
theocratic government and Ayatah Kmeni
was the first leader. And what did it
look like in case you're wondering?
Okay, Ayatah
Humeni, the former Supreme Leader of
Iran.
That's what he looked like. If you want
to see what he looked like when he was
younger, I'm sure we'll be able to find.
Yeah, that's what he looked like when he
was younger. When he was a young man,
these are two images. Um, which one is
it? Yeah. Okay. This is him through the
ages through through through the years.
This is another way of looking at it.
Yep.
So that was his that's how he progressed
in life. He his appearance. So what is
the story behind Ayatahi?
So his grandfather
was a Shia scholar from present day
Uttar Pradesh. Kinur village in Uttar
Pradesh. Where is Kinur village? Let's
let's let's find out.
Okay, let's go to the map
and see.
Okay, Kinur,
Kinur, Uttar Pradesh.
Okay, we will first zoom out and zoom
back in.
So, it is not far from Lacnau.
Okay. And this is the place
Kinthur.
So that is where uh his grandfather was
from his grandfather was from this
village in Uttar Pradesh. We'll zoom
out. Okay. Now
but how did they end up in Iran is the
question. So
Mr. Kmeni's grandfather say Ahmed Musafi
Hindi was a Shia scholar from Kinur in
Uttar Pradesh and he was not fond of the
British rule over India. So in around
Shy Ahmed Musavi Hindi left India and he
went to Iraq. He went to Najaf and
Karbala in Iraq and uh there is there
are there are Shia schools or seminaries
over there and he first went there but
then he went to Iran and he settled down
in the ta in the town of Kain Kumain. So
let's find out where is Kmen. We saw
where is Kin. Now let's find out where
is Kumain.
Okay.
Kain Iran.
Um
must be this I suppose.
So this is Hain in Iran and that's where
his grandfather
um eventually settled. Okay. So he left
India because he was not a big fan of
British rule of the British occupation
of India. uh he did not feel safe or he
did not feel happy and that's why he
first went to Iraq and then he
eventually settled down in humain in
Iran and that is how
ayatahi
had an Indian grandfather
and he did acknowledge his Indian
origins but he was but he was not a
great friend of India let's understand
that okay so the the origins are very
clear his from his paternal side there
is Indian origin but when it comes to u
modern day India so in the 20th century
India you already had the Kashmir issue
right Mr. Neu gave away a significant
portion of the territory of Kashmir to
Pakistan then he went to the UN instead
of taking it back and that's why this
dispute still this this issue this
dispute still exists that Pakistan
occupies Indian territory that's the
dispute so that dispute exist existed in
the 20th century also and Mr. Kmeni
Ayatah Kmeni he sometimes referred
to Kashmir in in reference to Palestine.
So he would say that the that if the
Muslim if the Islamic world were united
then the Jews would not have Palestine
and the Hindus would not have Kashmir.
Right? So yeah that was his that was his
views about Kashmir.
So anyway, yes uh no no no question that
Ayatahi had Indian origin from his
grandfather's side from Uttar Pradesh
near Laknau.
Poorest defeated Alexander says if India
is the greatest civilization why did
India have no great structures like the
pyramids?
Well I could ask you something else in a
similar way. The United States is the
greatest uh civilization today or empire
today. Why don't they have great
structures like the pyramids? The
British Raj was the greatest empire
in the 19th century. Why didn't they
have pyramids?
Right? Rome had a great great empire.
Why did they not build pyramids? The
Greeks are a great civilization. The
Chinese are great civilization. Why did
not they don't build great structures
like the pyramids?
So is the benchmark of a civilization's
greatness going to be how large a
pyramid they can build?
Why is it so? Every civilization has its
own benchmarks, has its own way of
expressing its culture,
has its own way of expressing
its civilizational outlook, right? Um so
in Egypt they built pyramids. We're not
quite sure what the pyramids were built
for, but it took tremendous amount of
labor for God knows how many years or
decades to build those structures and
the labor they used was mostly slave
labor. Now in India, we did not have
slavery. If you ask Google, they will
say yes, you had slavery in India. You
had dasas. But Google is so stupid
because it is just a computer that it
doesn't understand that the word Dasa
means servant not slave. Some of our
emperors had the name Dasa.
Some of our kings had had the name Dasa
in their names. The the term Dasa in
their names. Who was King Dvodas? The
father of King Sudas who won the battle
of the 10 kings. Why was he called
Sudas? Does it mean good slave? Sudas
yeah obviously not it means good servant
good servant of the people
so dasa doesn't mean slave now coming
back to your question we in India did
not have slavery
right we never had slavery and to build
something as as magnificent let's say
and as as as enormous as the pyramids
would not be feasible because it served
no purpose in society
It gave no value to society. What is the
point of building a gigantic pyramid?
What what good does it do for society?
In India, we build we built structures
that served a good purpose in society.
We had temples. Temples were not just
places of worship. They were educational
institutions. That's why we had temples
all across the length and the breadth of
the country.
Then you had, you know, the Mahaviharas
and so much more. We we had assembly
halls. We had great baths like in the
Saraswati Hindu period of our history.
So all the great monumental architecture
that we constructed it served the
people. It served society. It served the
civilization. I think that is more of an
indicator of a civilization's greatness
than constructing
gigantic
monuments that serve no real purpose for
society. Ask yourself, what purpose did
the pyramids serve in Egyptian society?
Maybe some kind of we we're not quite
sure what the pyramids were for because
see, they were not burial places of the
of the kings of Egypt, the pharaohs. The
kings of Egypt were buried in in a
different location.
So, we're not quite sure what purpose
the pyramids served. But the pyramids
did not serve any useful purpose in
society as far as we can see. Did not
produce it was not a machine that
produced goods.
We we don't know what it what it did.
But it it required so much labor which
was wasteful actually. That labor could
have been used for something else. So
that's how Indian civilization is. It is
different from Egyptian civilization.
It's different from other civilizations.
And overall I would say that the
greatness of a civilization cannot be
measured in the size
of the monuments it builds.
The greatness of a civilization is
measured in how long it it exists and
how good the quality of life is
as long as it exists. That's how you
measure the greatness of a civilization
from my perspective.
Real Vladimir Putin says Jews after the
fall of the Third Reich in 1945 were in
a pretty bad condition. Then how did
they manage to create modern day the
modern day nation of Israel and get all
this support from the United States?
What did the US gain from it? So you see
the Jews, the Jewish diaspora has been
present in Europe for about 2,000 years.
uh and they lived in various parts of
Europe and they were persecuted from
time to time. There was tremendous
anti-semitism that was you know done
against them. They also did well in
various parts of Europe and they became
pretty wealthy. They became pretty
influential. They were money lenders.
They were merchants. They were wealthy.
They would even lend money to kings to
finance to finance their various
military and other campaigns. So Jews,
see Jews fared much better than the
Romani people
in Europe. The Romani people were were
subjected to all kinds of horrific
atrocities. The Jews fared better. They
also had to face massacres. They also
had to face all kinds of horrible
accusations. They also had to face
pogros, the Jews in various parts of
Europe from time to time. But they also
were able to be successful in Europe.
Now,
a lot of Jews migrated to the United
States in the 19th century.
And a significant portion of the Jews
that migrated to the US in the 19th
century,
they settled down
on the east coast. A lot of them settled
down in New York City.
More than 20 more than 30% of the
population of New York City was Jewish.
Let's let's fact check what I'm just
saying here.
I should not. Yeah, let's let's fact
check that. What percentage of
NYC
population uh population
population
was Jewish
in 1880? Let's see.
Over 6.6%.
Really? What about 1800?
Do we have figures less than 1%. What
about 1900
70 to 20 [laughter]
1900 17 to 20% of the city's total
population. What about 1930? So you can
see there's a big influx of Jewish
people. So by 1930 the Jewish population
in New York City was about 27 about 30%.
Okay. So there were a lot of wealthy
Jewish people. So they they didn't when
they came to the US many of them were
poor. They had escaped Germany. They
they had escaped various parts of Europe
and they wanted to settle down in this
new country and start a new life and
they were pretty industrious.
They they took initiative and they
became successful. Some of them came
with some money. So eventually by 1930
or something about 30% of the population
of New York City is Jewish and many of
them are really really wealthy. So
that's one thing we have to understand
that yeah Jews
were in terrible condition in Europe
after the fall of the third Reich and
during the Second World War because of
what the Nazis did to them, what
Hitler's Nazis did to the Jews. No
question. But in the United States, Jews
were increasingly wealthy. Okay. Now
there was in the 19th century the
beginning of the Zionist movement the
movement for a nation of the Jewish
people. There was this journalist an
Austri Austrohungarian journalist called
Theodor Herzel
who uh because of rising anti-semitism
and other issues he
essentially gave Zionism a clear
political program. He said that Jews
needed a state of their own. Jews were a
nation in their own right and they
needed a physical geographical state or
nation of their own. And the first
Zionist congress happened in Basil in
1897 in which uh this guy he published a
pamphlet arguing for the uh
for the creation of a Jewish nation. He
said that his he and his and his allies
they said that their goal was to create
a Jewish nation in what was then called
Ottoman Palestine, right? And they built
this international organization, Zionist
organization to pursue this objective
diplomatically
um through settlement of Jews.
So during the sec during the first world
war, okay, the first world war is the
1910s. During this time, the British
captured
the region of Palestine. It was then
called Palestine from the Ottoman
Empire. And Britain then started to see
began to see Zionism
as something that was in alignment with
British strategic interests in the
region.
So in 1917, the British government
issued something called the Balfur
declaration. It said that it was in
favor of the establishment of a Jewish
nation in this region called Palestine.
And they said that they would not be
they would not do anything that would be
bad for the people who who already live
there, the Arab people who already live
there. Right? So that was the Balfur
declaration and after the first world
war ended, Turkey was carved up and the
League of Nations which was the pre
precursor of the United Nations, it gave
Britain the mandate of Palestine. So
Britain would manage and administer and
rule Palestine and that's when Jewish
immigration starts in the region in the
1920s30s 1940s. There is there are
multiple waves successive waves of
Jewish immigrants coming into what is
what was then called Palestine and
settling over there. Right? And why were
they settling over there? Because there
was this rise of anti-semitism in Europe
and know eventually because of the
German the Nazi you know atrocities
against Jews. was the Holocaust, right?
So the Jews would then settle in
Palestine. They would purchase land.
They would create agricultural colonies.
They would they even created uh you know
militias, armies and uh political
parties, all of that. And they created
eventually a separate Jewish society
alongside the Arab majority at the time
in in what was then called Palestine.
And this began to spark violence,
resentment from the locals. And uh this
began to start violence between the
Arabs and the Jews. Okay.
So then the second world war ends and in
a couple of years later the UN general
assembly it said that part it it said
that part Palestine should be
partitioned into two separate states
nations a Jewish nation and an Arab
nation [snorts] and Jerusalem would be
under international administration. So
the Jewish leaders, the Zionist leaders,
they accepted this plan. But the Arab
leaders were unhappy with it. They said
it is unjust and they rejected it. So
after the vote for the partition,
fighting broke out between the uh Arabs
and the Jews in Palestine. And once the
British withdrew by 1948, this escalated
into a full-scale war. So is the state
of Israel was was declared or proclaimed
in 1948 and immediately once this
happens all the Arab nations they attack
Israel and that is the 1948 ArabIsrael
war and Israel gets support from its
allies and there is a ceasefire
armistice in 1949 and by the time the
ceasefire happens the nation of Israel
controls about 80% of the former mandate
of Palestine the British mandate of
Palestine much more than the area that
was given to it by the United Nations
and it is said that several hundred,000
Palestinians were expelled or they had
fled from the territory. So that
essentially is how the nation of Israel
was formed. And uh even though Jews had
they had to face terrible terrible
circumstances in Europe because of the
Holocaust, because of the uh policies of
the Third Reich, the Jews in the United
States were very wealthy and they were
able to uh support the Jews who needed
help. And eventually um because of US
support Israel was able to survive
and uh that is the story. What does the
US gain from it? The US gains an ally in
the Middle East, right? Uh
see the Middle East is a very important
region geopolitically from the
perspective of energy security because
much of the world's oil petroleum comes
from this region and uh it makes sense
for the US to have a very strong ally in
the region, right? And a powerful ally
in the region. So it makes sense for the
US.
Okay.
Amisha says, "If Roman society was so
stratified, why did the Romans pour so
much funds, money, whatever into public
infrastructure that benefited everyone?"
Good question. Great question actually.
See, Roman society was a hierarchical
society. Okay? It's it was like a
pyramidal structure. At the very top,
you had people called the patricians,
wealthy citizens at the very top. Then
you had people who were called the
equites, the plebeians. Then you had the
freed men. And at the bottom you had the
slaves. And slaves constituted very
large percentage of the population of
Roman society. And there were freed men
who were former slaves who had been
freed. So they were one rung above the
slaves. The the slaves were not free.
The freed men were free and that sort of
thing. So you had a pyramidal structure,
a strictly sharply rigidly hierarchical
society. you had in Rome. And despite
the situation of the society being so
hierarch hierarchical,
many major public works, amenities like
baths and fountains and roads and sewers
and aqueducts and even entertainment
u uh you know buildings dedicated to
entertainment such as uh amphitheaters
etc. These were constructed
and they were made accessible to large
segments of the urban urban population
mostly in Rome. Not just the upper
classes but large segments of the urban
population. Now what is the why do that
when you have all the power all the
money? Why do so much public works and
and and give so much
nice stuff to the to the people who are
not in power who don't have the money or
the power? Why do that? Right? So in
Roman society, wealthy people, wealthy
individuals, they were expected to fund
public works, okay? Baths and theaters
and temples and libraries and
amphitheaters.
Um they would even distribute food to
the po poor people. This was done as
visible gifts to their communities and
these would be recorded. Okay. So by
doing this prominent Roman citizens
would would gain honor. They would gain
social status because I have so much
money I'm able to donate and do all this
work. And they all this work would be
commemorated in inscriptions and
monuments. That was a means of attaining
glory on the on the in the historical
record in monuments in inscriptions on
monuments. Right? And all all of this
was very important. It really mattered
in the Roman culture the elite culture
of Rome. Now Rome had two periods. One
is the republic. The other is the
imperial period of Rome. The imperial
period begins with Augustus,
right? With with the ascent of Augustus.
Octavian becomes Augustus. He was
Caesar's uh chosen hair. Uh Caesar was
the bridge between the republican period
and the imperial period. So during the
republican period of of of Rome, if you
were an ambitious
highborn person, a noble, if you were
ambitious, you sought high office. If
you wanted to gain more power, more
influence, you would use public works
as a win as a as a as a means to win
popular support and outshine your your
adversaries, your rivals. Uh nobles
would would organize games. They would
organize games in amphitheaters, you
know, gladiatorial combat or other
things. That sort of thing. Uh, similar
to what we have today like football
games and cricket games, you know, it
keeps the public's mind occupied away
from what really matters. You're going
to keep watching your IPL. You're going
to keep watching your cricket match,
football match. You're going to keep
obsessing over this rivalry, that
rivalry, my favorite player is this guy,
your favorite player is this guy. I hate
that guy. I like this guy.
those little petty minor insignificant
things consume the time and the energy
and the thoughts of the majority of the
people. The same thing was also the case
in Rome where they had these great
gladiators and they would organize these
great games, right? And whoever
organized this, you know, they were able
to outshine their rivals.
So, and it's not just games. You you
built aqueducts, you built roads, you
built highways, you built temples, all
of that. So
by doing this, you were able to gain
support from the public because public
support still mattered. You were able to
gain votes. You were able to able to
bring people into your into your inner
circle of power. Yeah. It gave you
prestige. It gave you long-term family
reputation. And the the poor masses,
the population, they also received
tangible benefits. So if you became
powerful and you were super wealthy,
they would not be too jealous. They
would not be likely to stick a dagger
between your ribs from in the night,
right? That sort of thing. So that's
another reason why, you know, so much uh
infrastructure was built. In this public
infrastructure, it also helped to
maintain
law and order in Rome. Okay? Because if
you have [snorts]
good roads, if you have temples where
people can go and worship, if you have
amphitheaters where you can go and watch
gladiators kill each other, if you have
a reliable water supply from the
aqueducts, if you have good sew sewage
systems, if you had if you have good
public baths, if you have all of these
things, it is going to bring potential
the potential for discontent
significantly drastically down. It will
also limit disease. If you have high
quality water supplies, sewage systems,
public baths, all that, then diseases,
the incidence of diseases will will also
go down. And this once again will keep
the public happy. So all of this, the
effect it had is that it made the
populations more governable. Okay? And
when it comes to roads and bridges and
ports and harbors, well, these served
geopolitical and military purposes.
Okay? They helped military movement.
They helped people they helped the
administration collect taxes from
various provinces, far away provinces.
They they helped the administration and
the Roman Empire conduct long-distance
trade between its provinces and between
its vasals and the the core state.
Right? So this made the state more
powerful. It made the empire more
powerful. It made the landowning elites
wealthier. Right? So these are the
reasons why Roman society despite being
so stratified etc so hierarchical it
still spent so much money on public
infrastructure which benefited the
larger society because you have to keep
the people happy that way you will have
an orderly and governable society. If
the people are unhappy if they are
discontented
if their their living conditions are
unbearable then you're going to have
anarchy. No matter how many soldiers you
have, you can't you can't govern the
people who are in the millions. So
that's the reason why the Romans poured
so much wealth into public
infrastructure into public works.
Abijit Shira Rajish says the loose baggy
shalwar pants worn in the northwest
Indian subcontinent with its folds and
creases seem quite reminiscent of some
styles of draping a traditional Indian
dohi. However, Wikipedia claims the
shalwir is central Asian in origin. Is
this right? Is it a coincidence? Let's
find out what Wikipedia has to say about
this. Okay. So, we'll go to Google and
say shall shalwir
ah
shalwir. Let's see. Shalwir kamse.
So, um shalwars are trousers that are
typically why we know what they are.
Okay. Thank you very much. So, what does
Wikipedia say? The shalwir and kamse
were introduced into south Asia by
arriving Muslims
uhhuh in the north in the 13th century
at first worn by Muslim women then their
use was widely spread and made blah blah
blah blah blah. So it says that
salvaries came into India in the 13th
century. It was brought by Muslims. It
was first worn by women. This is what
Wikipedia claims. Now this is nonsense.
Let me destroy this this claim once and
for all.
Have you heard of Emperor Kanishka?
Emperor Kanishka the Great.
Kaneska
the great. Here we have it. So what does
Emperor Kaneska the Great look like?
Let's go to Wikipedia itself. Look at
this. What is our emperor wearing? What
is that?
He's wearing a Shalwar Kamese. He's
wearing a coat. He's wearing trousers
and he's wearing boots.
Right? Do we have other? See once again
what is this? He's wearing boots. He's
wearing trousers. He's wearing a coat
kind of thing which which goes all the
way down. This is the original form of
the shalwar kamse. This is from
sulkotal. See once again what is he
wearing?
What is he wearing? This is a this is
nothing but the shawwar kamse. So
Wikipedia is lying to you. See once
again what's he wearing here? Shalwar
Kamese
here once again it's Shalwar Kam. So the
Wikipedia the the claim of Wikipedia
that um Shalwar Kamese was brought into
India in the 13th century by invading
Muslims.
It is absolutely nonsense.
Emperor Kaneshka was wearing Shalwar
Kamese 2,000 years ago.
Now the question is what's the origin of
the So first of all we have debunked
Wikipedia's lies. It did not arrive into
India in the 13th century. It did not
come with invading Muslims. It was born
in India 2000 roughly. See 1900 years
ago Emperor Kaneska used to wear it. So
it doesn't mean that Emperor Kanishka
invented the Salvar Kamis. It would have
been in usage for a long time before
him. So at least 2,000 years ago Indians
were wearing the Svar Kamis. Now you can
say that Kaneshka was a foreigner. He
was a descendant of Kushans.
But he was an Indian emperor, right? He
governed he ruled India. He was Indian.
Most of his coins are Hindu coins. 1%
are Buddhist coins.
Much of the territory he governed was
Indian territory. And he fought on
behalf of India. He did more to serve
the Indian national and civilization
interest than any other emperor I can
almost think of. So he was absolutely
Indian. Sure his ancestors came from
what is now called Sinjang but they were
not Chinese. They were Kushans. The
Kushans can be regarded as the eastern
mostians.
The Skithians were of Indian origin. So
once again it's a round circle. Now
what's the origin of the Salvaries? Now
this is we're going to use logic and a
little bit of speculation for this. See
if you go to north India historical
north India the subcontinent then we are
talking about regions such as Gandhara
Afghanistan right present day
Afghanistan all the way to the borders
of Turkmanistan etc
and
1500 years ago this entire region was
Hindu Buddhist Hindu and Buddhist you
had Hindu monks and Buddhist monks and
Buddhas and viharas and whatnot tupas
all over the place.
When Schwanzang reached the Bameyan
Valley in present day Afghanistan, what
did he say? Did he say yes, I have
reached Afghanistan? No, he said thank
God I've reached India. Right? So that
was India.
The people were our people.
So now think about the climate in that
region, northern subcontinent.
It's cold
in Afghanistan today. In the summer it
can get quite dry and hot but the
winters are can be frighteningly cold
like seriously chilly. It snows most of
the winter in Kabul for example
and other parts of of of Gandhar. So the
Indians who lived there and other parts
of India like Chetal etc. do you think
they used to wear dotis in winter? Makes
no sense right? they would have worn
something that was suitable for the
climate.
So, it's possible that they would also
have worn something like the Salvaries,
but a heavier version of that, you know,
a thicker jacket, thicker coat and
thicker trousers and boots because if
you're going to walk around in the snow,
you can't be barefoot. You can't wear
slippers or sandals. You got to wear
boots that cover your feet.
And from the evidence we have from the
coins of Kaneshka, the Salvaries was
worn
during this time.
So
the way I see it, it's most likely a
northern Indian.
It's northern Indian attire.
Wikipedia will say whatever it says, we
don't have to believe in it. So one
clear unambiguous piece of evidence is
that Emperor Kaneska wore Sulvar Kamese.
And if he was wearing that at this about
what 1900 years ago, it means that it
was something that was commonly used
during his time, which means it would
have been commonly used for centuries
before him. So most likely there was no
Central Asian origin of this. Most
likely it was
northern Indian attire, attire that was
used that was worn in cold parts of the
Indian subcontinent such as Kashmir,
such as Gandhar, present day
Afghanistan,
etc.
Okay,
next question.
Nirj gi desai says when did crossing the
sea become a sin for Hindus? It is said
that Rammanujan was not ready to cross
the sea even though we already had sea
routes for trading with Africa, Middle
East, Europe etc. and we had navies like
the Maratas and the Cholas. So was this
taboo thing real or if so why did it
start? I'm not sure I have seen any
research paper or book that deals with
this this this taboo. So the taboo seems
to have been real in the in the last
couple of centuries
maybe last few centuries that if you
lost I mean you became
an outcast or something you would have
to beified or something if you cross the
sea. That sort of taboo did exist in the
past few centuries. Clearly and that is
so strange because India was a maritime
civilization.
When Raj Raj when Rajendra Chola crossed
the sea and
conquered free Vijaya did he break some
taboo? No.
Nobody said a thing about that. Right.
He did cross the Indian Ocean, the
western the eastern Indian Ocean, the
the Bay of Bengal. He went all the way
to Shir Vijaya, which is Indonesia
present day. He conquered the place and
he then he set things in order over
there and he came back. There was there
was no problem at that time.
Indians
arrived in Australia 5,000 years ago, 4
and a half thousand years ago. They
obviously arrived by sea. We know that
the the genetic footprint is still there
among the native uh Australian
populations. So Indians cross the ocean
almost 4 and a half thousand years ago.
And that is not just Indonesia, that's
all the way to Australia, Northern
Australia. Indians have had a presence
in Eastern Africa for centuries,
thousands of years essentially. East
Africa. If you look at East African
culture, the kind of
clothing the people wear, especially
ladies, it's very similar to what you
have in Gujarat, the Gujarati textiles.
If you see the the cuisine of places
like Kenya, Tanzania etc., it's very
Indian influenced cuisine. And you have
communities of Indians from western
India who have been living in in East
Africa for centuries if not millennia.
Vasco Dagama when he came when he
reached there he was able to reach India
because he was guided by an Indian
sailor.
So Indians were thriving in East Africa.
They would cross the ocean all the time
back and forth from India. They were
trading right? They were trading.
So Indians have been crossing. I mean
when it comes to the oldest literature
that we have in humanity in human
history the rigida it speaks about
ships with a 100 oes
you don't need a ship with 100 oes to
cross some river or to navigate a river
you don't need that ships with 100 oes
you need them in the high seas in the
high oceans where the where the ocean
can get rough so even thousands of years
ago when the rig weather was written
Indians were already
crossing the seas, the oceans.
So now that we have we understand this
history that India has always been a
maritime civilization, how did this
extremely strange taboo
become a thing in India? I'm not sure it
was if it was a taboo all across India
but it certainly seems to have been in
some parts of India. I mean Mr. Gandhi,
Mr. Mahindra Gandhi probably did not
probably may have faced this taboo and
so did Shinasa Rammanujan apparently.
So how did this happen is the question.
Now we like I said we don't have any
research papers. No historian has
bothered to look into this. So let's
think about it logically.
India was a maritime civilization.
Indians used to cross the oceans. But
something happened and this became a
taboo. What happened is the question.
Now what is the clue that we have? What
are the clues? The taboo is a recent
taboo.
Rajendra Chola crossed the ocean a
thousand years before today. Roughly
there was no taboo then. So 1,00 AD, no
taboo. But 1900 AD, taboo. Something
happened between 1,000 AD and 1900 AD.
What happened? I think we all know what
happened. The most traumatic event ever.
The foreign occupation of India. First
by the Turks and then by the British.
The Turks when they occupied India, they
were genocidal.
Hundreds of millions of Indians would
have been killed over the centuries.
And because of that the entire structure
of Indian society crumbled. It oified.
It was no no longer able to evolve
naturally the way society naturally
evolves.
And because there was this constant
constant threat of murder, genocide by
the Turks,
I I expect that the men folk of families
were expected to not go and cross the
oceans and they were expected to stay
stay back home and defend the family.
Most likely that's what happened. When
the nation is under foreign occupation,
you can't go trading.
You can't go and cross the ocean when
your your your family is at risk. They
are under the threat of the Turks. So
maybe that's why the taboo became a
thing. And that's why it was no longer
seen as reasonable behavior for somebody
to cross the ocean
and to go abroad in search of whatever
trade, adventure, whatever. It was no
longer responsible behavior. And if you
did that, you were no longer part of a
community. You're gone. Out outcast.
Maybe that's what happened.
That makes sense logically the way I see
it. Okay.
Uh
Amisha says, "Every great civilization
has declined when its culture of
openness is replaced by closed minds and
an aversion to questions. Western
civilization has flourished and
prospered precisely because it has cast
off the yoke. That's the Catholic Church
and allowed free thought. We in India
are in decline because of our because of
our culture has lost its ability to
question and innovate. We also prefer
shortcuts. It's is it is a historical
inevitability that and there is nothing
we can do about it. Do you agree that
this can be the reason for the decline
of Indian civilization? Okay. Multiple
reasons for the decline of Indian
civilization. You make some interesting
points here.
Multiple reasons.
First of all, we gradually lost a
sovereignty over our territory
with the expansion of the Turk
occupation of India. Starts with
Gandhar, starts with Afghanistan
about 1,000 years before today.
Afghanistan was the first part of the
subcontinent that fell and it was
primarily Buddhist at the time, which is
why it converted very rapidly to Islam.
So civilization, Indian civilization
switched off there. It becomes part of
Turk and Islamic civilization. Right?
Then slowly the Turks started
encroaching into various parts of India.
For 3 4 500 years the Rajputs fought
them, fought them, fought them.
Eventually the Turk Turks were able to
make inroads. They established the Delhi
Sultanate and then eventually the Muggal
Empire became a thing and they took over
very large parts of India. When you come
under foreign occupation,
your institutions are no longer able to
function. What institutions did we have
in India before the Turks came in? We
had monarchies. We had empires at times.
We had indigenous administrative
systems. We had an indigenous education
system that was the same more or less
across the subcontinent.
We had our own ways of of conducting
social rituals, marriages, weddings,
child births and so so many other
things. Right? When you are under
foreign occupation, none of these
things,
you're no longer free to do any of these
things unless the foreign occupiers
allow you to do it. The foreign
occupiers, they had a very clear purpose
in India to convert everybody to their
foreign religion and they went to the
extent of doing genocide in India
multiple times.
They destroyed all the temples. So the
entire education system that was built
around temples in northern India wiped
out. Only small scale temples with that
somehow survived. They were able to
function.
Then the indigenous administ
administrative system is gone. The great
uh universities are destroyed and
burned.
So when all your knowledge is destroyed,
when your system of education is
destroyed, when all your intellectuals
are killed off, when your kings are no
longer kings or they are killed off and
foreigners are ruling you, they are
imposing foreign laws on you,
then where can you have a culture of
openness? Where can you have a culture
where you can have free thought and free
debate?
When you are under threat of dying any
time, there's no free thought. There's
no free free debate. There's no
innovation.
There is no cultural manifestation of of
new cultural forms. Your music dies out.
Your dance forms die out. Your forced to
do weddings at in the middle of the
night otherwise the Turks will abduct
the girls.
So you see everything the entire society
oifies. It becomes calcified. It can't
evolve.
Right.
So that sort of thing happened
and that is the reason for the decline
of Indian civilization first of all.
Then you had the Europeans who who came
and took over. The British did that and
the British went multiple steps for f
further than the Turks. They said we
will not genocide the Indians. Yeah sure
we'll starve them to death and maybe a
few hundred million we can kill off like
that but we want to mentally coronize
the Indians. So they imposed they first
of all abolished the whatever was
surviving of the indigenous Indian
education system and then they made it
mandatory for you to have an English
medium education if you wanted a
government job and because they
completely de-industrialized India. The
only way to earn a livelihood was by
having a government job. But for that
you had to know English. You had to have
an English education based on the system
the British had imposed on you. So that
completely wiped out our society our our
culture
and it it it planted the seeds of mental
colonizers and mental slavery into the
minds of Indians and that education
system the British imposed still
continues today and it's an education
system based on wrote memorization
see how do you actually learn something
you learn by asking questions right but
in the Indian education system you're
not supposed to ask questions you're
supposed to answer questions so it is
completely killed off.
You know, critic the ability to think
critically, the ability to to learn
things on your own. You simply you're
not supposed to ask questions. You're
not supposed to learn things. You're not
supposed to think critically. You're
simply supposed to accept whatever you
told.
These are the reasons why our
civilization is dying. Now, when it
comes to culture, one of the most
important elements of civilization is
culture,
which manifests itself in multiple
forms. architecture,
dance, music,
all of that all of this is and and in
India in in a civilization like India
civilization all of this needs state
patronage
and today in today's 21st century
society even 20th century society there
has been almost no state patronage for
Indian cultural activities like dance
music nothing has evolved
Indian musicians are still playing the
same sitar they were playing 100 years
ago. The instruments haven't evolved
and the ganas are dying out. So because
there is no money now and the pe and and
the the masses they now watch the cheap
Bollywood music and whatn not that's why
Indian cultural forms like Indian
classical dances non-class dances
there's no actual distinction Indian
classical music all of this is simply
dying a slow gradual death
and the education system for it doesn't
teach you how to innovate how to
question so because of all these reasons
Indian culture Indian civilization is
declining and if this continu another 50
years will be finished. India will be
put note in history.
Okay, I still have a lot of questions
that I have chosen but I want to be able
to take them because I've already
crossed two hours. There are a lot a lot
more questions. Okay, let's take some
questions that you all have asked in the
live chat. Okay, I can see super chat a
whole bunch of super chats. Okay, what
do we have? have Anil Chri is a new
member. Welcome to the membership. Thank
you so much. Vsvs, namaste. Namaste.
Good to have you. Vsvs has gifted five
memberships. Thank you so much. You're
so kind. Very kind of you.
Vsvs have to deal with Kanglu Mia from
Super Slum Bangladesh. We'll deal with
them. Look, I know.
See
right now the relationship between India
and Bangladesh Bangladesh isn't good
because Bangladesh is now run by by
individuals who are puppets of a foreign
country and who are inimical to India.
And as we know there are horrible things
happening in Bangladesh right now. If
you are a Hindu in Bangladesh you don't
know whether you will be alive tomorrow
morning or not. That is the situation in
Bangladesh. So, we're going to have to
deal with this, but we're going to have
to deal with this judicially,
judiciously
because the last thing we should do
right now is to do military action
because that's what the West wants.
That's what the US wants so that they
can portray us as the same as Putin,
right? Even Putin is not wrong for for
what he has done. But whatever. So,
yeah, we have to deal with them. How
should we deal with Bangladesh? The
first thing we need to do is to expel
all the illegal Bangladeshi infiltrators
who are sitting in India.
That's the first thing we we must do. We
need to expel them all. I think some
action is happening on that front. But
there are about 100 million possibly
Bangladeshes, illegal Bangladeshi
infiltrators who are embedded across
India. We need to get rid of these
illegal infiltrators. I have nothing
against legal immigration. you come
through the proper channels, apply for a
visa, get a visa, then come legally. I'm
you're welcome. But my issue is with the
illegal infiltrators. They need to be
dealt with. So that's the first thing
India needs to do. Visa Bangladesh and
then yeah, we need to pressurize
Bangladesh to to to safeguard
the Hindu population and so on.
Okay. WBR says, "What was the ancient
and medieval age equivalent of nukes or
was there none with the deterrence and
destruction capability of a nuke and
nuclear weapons? Are they the first kind
of their thing in history?" There was no
ancient equivalent of nuclear weapons.
There was nothing in ancient times that
could unleash that much destruction.
Nothing.
Um that sort of destructive power has
only become readily widely available in
militaries in the past
couple of hundred years. And it started
with gunpowder. Gunpowder and
projectiles that explode that sort of
thing.
But even those explosives were nothing
compared to the kind of devastation a
nuclear weapon can unleash. So there was
no equivalent in ancient times and
medieval times of nuclear weapons. There
is nothing that has ever existed that is
comparable to nuclear weapons first of
their kind in human history. Indeed.
An subramanyam says one historical
ruler lesson individuals can apply
today. What is one historical pattern
you you actually change your daily
behavior.
One historical ruler lesson individuals
can apply today.
One individ one one historical lessons
individuals can apply today. Um
let me think there are so many lessons
that we can learn from history. But
you're talking about individuals not
nations.
Well
one [laughter]
look this doesn't apply to everybody of
course.
One historical lesson that is relevant
even to people is that power always
trumps wealth.
If you're powerful,
it's it's so essentially it's better to
be powerful than to be wealthy. If you
are powerful, then wealth will anyway
automatically flow to you. But if you
are wealthy, no matter how much wealth
you have, think about this example, Jack
Ma of China, the wealthiest man in
China, right? How much power did he
actually have?
A low ranking Chinese Communist Party
official in in any given city actually
has more power than Jakma and can put
Jakma under under bar, you know, behind
bars. And that's essentially what
happened to Jakma, right? He had a big
downfall.
So power always trumps wealth. That's
one historical lesson that applies to
everybody. Um is there any pattern that
changed my behavior? I'm not sure. I'm
not sure.
Lakshadep
becomes a new member. Thank you very
much. Let us all welcome Lakshadep to
the membership of the channel. Thank you
so much. Sorab says recent Epstein files
release. So look, I it's a very new
thing that's happened. I think uh it's
all redacted. A lot of it is just black
black lines and stuff. I haven't even
had the time to look into it.
So yeah, I can't really comment at this
point in time. Yeah. And this is anyway
not a historical matter. It's a it's
more of a it's more of a local matter
within the United States and it will
have some geopolitical ramifications
based on depending on what kind of
individuals are exposed as part of this
uh this disclosure. if it is if it can
be called a disclosure. I'm not sure
about if it's a disclosure or not. But
yeah, so it's so so it's too early to
speak about this at this point in time.
Let some time go by. Let people analyze
what actually has been disclosed. What
has been redacted, we can't say, but
what's been disclosed. Maybe some people
will analyze that. I won't be doing the
analysis. It's not something that
interests me that much, but I'll keep an
eye on it to see what kind of names come
out. So, we'll see.
WBR says, "What's your opinion on the
person on my profile pick?" Well, a
tragic person, you know, he used to be a
chef. He used to be a restaurant, then
he became the head of the Vagnner group.
Yes. Mr. Yvgrio Gojin
and then he sadly tragically died in a
plane crash. What's my opinion? Well, he
did serve his nation. He served his
nation and he died the death of a
warrior.
Yeah, that's what I can say.
Uh, Leroy Jenkins Kins says, "Are Jats
ironic or indicetically
Jats are the Jats?" I like I answered in
great detail a while ago. The Jats are
related to the Gate and the Masagate
tribes. Those were skitsian tribes. If
you ask Wikipedia, the skits are ironic.
So if you want to go by the Wikipedia
definition, the Jats are ironic then.
Iranic. But if you look at the Jats, do
they look ironic? They look indic.
So what does that tell you? That tells
you that the Skitians were also Indic,
not Iranic. See, there is this big
movement right now to deny the Indian
and Hindu origins of everything. So
everything
I mean Iran is this and India is that
big, but everything is irranic. Whatever
is in Central Asia, why? Whatever
populations exist in Central Asia that
speak Indo-Aran languages or
Indo-Iranian languages, they're going to
be classified
always as Iranic. So that's an issue
that these historians and other
individuals have. They want to deny the
Indian and Hindu origins of everything.
But the truth is that the Jats are
indically
and culturally and linguistically etc.
If they see the Jats are a very large
population. If they spoke any Iranic
language then the language would still
be spoken today but they speak Indo-aran
languages. None of them speaks
any so-called irranic language. So the
answer is the jats are indicants
to destroy most ancient Ara range. I
have no idea. This is not a historical
question. Today we are talking about
history and I am not aware of what's
going on over here. I have not looked
into it. So yeah, Parthonon says, "Why
do Indian brahinss look like southern
Europeans?" I can show you brahinss who
don't look like southern Europeans. Why
are you generalizing everything sir?
[laughter]
Don't generalize everything. Who says
all Indian brahinss look like southern
Europeans? Shinwasa
Rammanojanjunjanjunjanjunjanjunjanjunj
did he look like southern European?
Let's see what shinasa ramanojun looked
like. Okay.
Shini Shini Vasan
Shinasa Ramanujan. So does this fine
gentleman look southern European?
Shinas Ramanujan was a Brahman.
So my point is let's not generalize
things. You I can show you a 100 counter
examples. There's no such thing.
Do I look like a Southern European? I'm
not a Brahmin.
Okay, Bali today says, "Was Nazis
were the Nazis way ahead in propaganda
than communists?"
Well, the Nazis had the propaganda
ministry and they did a reasonably good
job, I suppose, for the time. But see,
today at the end of the day, you have to
look at the long-term impact of their
propaganda. Today, everybody rightfully
regards the Nazis as monsters. Their
propaganda has failed. But the
communists there are so many people who
worship communists.
There are so many people who regard uh
Mahatong as a great great guy. There are
so many people people who regard Joseph
Stalin as a great guy. There are so many
people who believe in the religion that
KL Marx created.
So I think communist propaganda has been
way more successful than Nazi
propaganda.
uh Sanker says how China grew land with
Mongols Turks next to it.
So the expansion of the Chinese empire
happened at various points in time. They
did a lot of expansion eastwards. They
gobbled up Manuria. There were no
Mongols or Turks there. The Manchus are
a different people. Eventually the
Manchus ruled China. The last dynasty to
rule China was a Manchu dynasty. Right?
U the Mongol Empire was there for only a
while and then it dissipated. It
weakened. The Mongol Empire conquered
China. It gave China the Yuan dynasty
which was a Mongol dynasty.
And then the Mongol Empire, it just
crumbled and fragmented like all empires
eventually do. And that's when China
took over parts of Mongolia and Russia
took over parts of Mongolia as well. And
then China used the claims
started claiming territory that the Yuan
dynasty, the Yuan Empire had had. So
look, it's it's a process that happened
over multiple centuries. Once the Mongol
Empire was no longer a major force, the
Chinese were able to take over. And the
Turks,
well, yeah, Sing Jang has some Turks,
but those Turks were not that powerful.
And of course, they did rebel against
the Chinese in the middle of the 19th
century. And the Chinese dealt with that
very harshly. The Chinese knew how to
deal
with the Turks. There's only one way the
Chinese know how to deal with any any
population group that uh that challenges
their hgemony. They try to wipe them out
of existence.
So yeah, long story. I can't explain
everything in detail right now over here
because that is something that that that
encompasses like
600 700 years.
UX Glowha says why do coins have ridges
along around the edges?
Okay, let's see.
Uh let's see. Morian coins
Morian coins. Do Morian coins have
ridges around the edges? No. No, no,
sir. No, sir. Okay. What about um
Kushan?
Kushan coins. Well, you see
there are no ridges around. There is
some decoration for sure, but there are
no ridges around the edges or Kushan
coins.
No ridges. What about Gupta coins?
Gupta coins. Once again, Gupta coins.
You will not find ridges around the
edges.
So in India, coins have historically not
had ridges around the edges. Are you
talking about coins from some other part
of the world?
But see, I I showed you multiple
examples of big Indian empires that have
not had coins with ridges around the
edges. Maybe you're talking about some
other part of the world. Well, it
depends on the local context etc.
Don't know.
Okay. VPS says Ashit Tagur
sir not getting tech
not getting tech job asked 100 companies
every day and did not get response sub
are up for experienced candidate. What
does this have to do with history first
of all?
Okay. Anyway, let me just since you've
asked,
you're not getting a tech job. You asked
100 companies every day. Well, there
must be some reason for it, right? Maybe
you aren't experienced enough. I see the
problem is I don't know you personally.
I don't know your background. I don't
know your track record. I don't know
your CV.
I don't know what kind of job you're
looking for. So, I how can I answer your
question? How can I give you a solution?
If you want me to give a workable
solution or some kind of way forward,
some kind of guidance, then first of
all, I need to understand your
background, your personal history and
your current circumstances.
Only then can I give you any kind of
guidance.
So all I can say in the absence of any
of that information is don't give up. If
there are some deficiencies in your
record, maybe the CV isn't strong or
whatever, address those things.
Work hard, but also work smart.
And if you don't get a tech job, look
for some other kind of job. There's
always a solution,
right? There's always a solution to
every problem. So, be creative.
Expand your horizons.
Try to find a solution. Don't take no
for an answer. And if this is not
working out, look for plan B, plan C.
That's what I would say. All right, sir.
All the best. All the best. I wish you
the best. I I wish you success.
Shiraat says, "Can you explain the
conflict? Can you explain about the
conflict in Yugoslavia and how that what
led to the break up of that country?"
See, I can go into this in great
excruciating detail which can take hours
or I can tell you what actually is the
deal.
In 1991 roughly, the USSR lost the Cold
War. The USSR broke up, right? And the
United States took over. They they they
installed
a pizza loving puppet.
Boris. No, not pizza loving. Vodka is
vodka. Vodka loving puppet. Boris Yelim.
So they had won the cold war. They This
was the uniolar moment for the US. They
could do whatever they wanted and they
said we will dismantle everything the
Soviets created.
The nation of Yugoslavia
was a protectorate of the USSR.
They said the the USSR made this. We
will break it up. And that's why they
broke it up. This conflict was
completely artificially
induced. Of course, you had these
ethnicities in the Balkans that those
ethnic issues go back centuries and all
of that is the consequence of the
Ottoman Empire's occupation of the
Balkans.
The conflict within the Bos Bosnians and
the Croats and the Serbs and the the
Kosovoirs and so on. All these issues go
back centuries and all you have to do is
to reignite that. So they they said we
will destroy Yugoslavia and that's what
they did and all these little nation
states came out of that. Croatia
north Macedonia
um Albania was never part of it but so
on. So what I can tell you in brief is
the US did this. The US broke Yugoslavia
up
and then there was this you know that
conflict that happened in the 1990s. You
had the siege of Sarah Evo. You had the
battle of Mustar. You had all kinds of
atrocities that happened there.
Yeah. So that it's it's pretty
convoluted history if I were to go into
detail. But essentially the big picture
situation is that the US decided that we
can do whatever we want. So we will
break up Yugoslavia. That's it. Vir
Kamat says I recently discovered that
the Rango script of Easter Island is
almost identical to the Indust script.
Something very interesting to share with
the viewers. Is it evidence of IVC
sailing expedition? We don't have the
answer to this question. No question.
The wrongo script is very similar to the
Saraspati Hindu script. It's it's like
let's see that right.
Okay. Wrongo wrong
indust.
Okay.
So if you look here, Indust Valley East
Island, Indust Valley, East Island, if
you see see the comparison, it's like
almost identical with some small minute
minor differences, right?
So clearly it's almost like a mirror
image. The wrong script script of Easter
Island is like almost like a mirror
image of the more way more ancient
Saraspati Hindu script. Is this evidence
of Indians having sailed to Eastern
Island? Now, let's look at where this
island is. It's in the middle. It's in
the heart of the South Pacific. Let's go
to uh Google Maps and let's go to the
South Pacific. Okay.
Rapanui. Where is Rapanui?
Hungaroa.
Um
this is Easter Island. Yeah, it belongs
it it belongs to Chile. So if I zoom
out, okay, if I place a pin there,
sorry,
if I zoom out, you will find that it's
in the middle of nowhere. And how far is
it from India? Let's let's measure the
distance. Okay. From let's say
um let us say from from the east coast
of India somewhere over here and let's
measure the distance
to here roughly it's about 18,000
kilometers
18,000 kilometers. Now is it possible
that Indians
4,000 5,000 years ago traveled 80,000 km
and went there? I think it's highly
unlikely. But then how did the script
end up? That's a big mystery. So is it
evidence of IVC sailing expedition? Not
necessarily.
It is evidence of a sailing expedition
only if you find evidence of a ship or
actual evidence of Indians having been
there. Maybe skeletal evidence, maybe
some other kind of actual hard
archaeological evidence. We have no such
thing. So maybe it means that that maybe
it could possibly mean that the people
who lived on Easter Island
in the past they maybe they lived
somewhere else maybe they came from
somewhere else and wherever they came
from maybe there was contact there
with the people of ancient India maybe
it's like maybe that could explain it
but right now as of now we don't have
the answers we only have questions
okay
how long has it been it's in 2 and 1/2
hours. WBR says some many say Ukraine
was created by linen and commis. Do you
agree
Ukraine?
Look,
was Ukraine created by commies and
Lenin? The the Ukrainian SSR was a
constituent unit of the USSR.
SSR means Soviet Socialist Republic. So
all these in India we have states like
you know Punjab, Rajasthan, Maharashtra,
Tamil Nadu, Kerala and so on.
So we have states in India in the USSR
you had SSRs, Soviet Socialist
Republics, you had a Tajik SSR, you had
a Ukrainian SSR, you had various SSRs
all over the place.
Now this designation of the region of
Ukraine as a Soviet Socialist Republic
SSR was definitely done by the Chinese
by the by the Soviet Communist Party.
But Ukraine was historically a region
and it was designated as a special
separate region, separate SSR because
the Ukrainian people speak a slightly
different language.
So it is just a historical fact but the
Ukraine war is a whole different thing.
Abida Singh says your thoughts about
Tamil Nadu future both politically and
spiritually after. No I'm not taking
this question. This has nothing to do
with history and I don't talk about
Indian politics. I stay away from it.
See I can't fight every battle in the
world. I talk about history,
geopolitics, science, very very vast
domains and I stick to that. I am not
going to discuss Indian politics. I I'm
sorry but I don't do that. It's a matter
of policy. I don't discuss Indian
politics and anyway this is a session
about history. So please I have to
remind people every time and people will
still disregard what I say that when I
do a history session let's talk about
history. Let's not talk about every
other thing in under the under the world
under the sun. Right? So anyway I will
not be able to take this question. Sorry
about that. I apologize.
Biju Sika says why USSR was considered
superpower. It was not like the USA who
could invade any country in the world
within 24 hours.
The USSR
was considered a superpower because it
had the ability to destroy any part of
the world it wanted. That's number one.
Number two, it was
an industrial superpower. It had a
massive industrial base. Thirdly, it had
the world's largest territory with about
half of the world's natural resources.
It had a frighteningly powerful
military,
maybe the largest standing military
after the Chinese eventually. So,
because of a variety of factors, it was
rightfully called a superpower.
Technologically incredibly advanced for
its time. For the longest time, they
were ahead of the US in the space race.
Very high quality science and technology
research happening over there.
Super powerful military, way more
powerful than China. Huge area, all the
resources you can want and a massive
nuclear arsenal. Clearly, it deserved to
be called a superpower. Bijua says, "Who
was Katherine the Great? Why is she
still celebrated in Russia even though
she was German?
She was a tsina in Russia, a female sar.
She [clears throat and cough]
she is celebrated because she
brought Russia to a certain level of
status in power. She was German indeed
and she kind of ousted her own husband
who was Assar and uh but she overall did
a good job of of of uh of ruling Russia
and Russia became significantly powerful
and and and the prestige of Russia
increased around this time which is why
she is called Katherine the Great. Yeah,
maybe we can do a separate you know
segment on Katherine the Great. pretty
interesting and significant and
consequential person. Maybe I can do
that in the future. But yeah, she was
one of the Russian Serenas. What 18th
century was it? Let's let's quickly look
up the exact time frame that we are
talking about. Katherine the Great. She
came after Peter, I'm sure.
Katherine the Great, Empress of Russia.
Correct. 18th century. Yes. And um
she definitely came after Peter the
Great, right? Peter the Great.
Peter the Great. Yes. Correct. Yes.
Yeah. So my rough chronological timeline
is correct. But uh so that's what I can
say in brief order. Uh
Zir Khan says it's shortsighted to
support legal Bangladeshi immigration. I
am not
I am not saying I support anything. I am
saying there is a difference between
legal and illegal.
Now legal immigration we can make it as
easy or as difficult as you want. I
would say make it as difficult as
possible for Bangladesh. Make it almost
impossible. That's fine. I am not
supporting Bangladesh coming into India.
I am saying please understand the
difference between legal and illegal.
That's all I am saying. I'm not
supporting it. Why are you construing
what I say as support for that? Why I
didn't say that? Please pay attention.
Language and words have nuances.
Please learn [clears throat] to
understand the the minute nuances
between something that's like surface
level and something that's slightly
deeper. I do not support Bangladeshes in
India. Bangladesh is a very problematic
nation today. We should not even have
legal immigration. We should make it as
difficult as possible.
But I am not okay.
Patriot Enfield says when will India
recognize Armenian genocide? That's not
our fight. We have when will we
recognize the Indian genocide?
We have suffered genocide at the hands
of the Turks and at the hands of the
British. We don't even recognize that
and you want to fight for the Armenian
genocide. It's like the people some
parts of certain Indians they have they
don't care about India but they want to
support Palestine. Right? It's like that
what you're saying here. Do you
understand what I'm saying?
Do you understand? We need to first
recognize our own history. The genocides
we have suffered. Why do we have to
fight every fight in the world? Why?
Maybe I mean I recognize the Armenian
genocide. India officially doesn't want
to get into all these matters right now.
But let's first recognize about what
what happened to our own people, right?
To our own ancestors, to our own
relatives.
Bijuya says, "English-speaking empires
have been dominating and ruling the
world for the past three centuries. What
special did they have that the Spanish
and French did not have? They were
better at the organized application of
violence. They were better at c creating
bureaucratic and governance systems that
lasted and grew and supported the
empire.
They were better at divide and rule.
They were better at at colonizing and
subjugating the defeated populations
than the Spanish were.
They did everything better than the
Spanish and the French.
And that's why they have dominated the
world. They created systems that worked.
And I' I've answered this question even
last week, the week before that. So,
yeah.
Okay.
James
James says,
"One second."
All right. James James says, "We
colonized you, yet you still behave
univilized. I was in Daravee recently.
Absolutely bad and horrible. Our trains
in the glorious stations in Bombay
Victoria terminus UNESCO site not
enough.
Okay.
Yes, Daravi. Well, um I suppose it may
not be great. Daravi,
um
the trains and glorious stations in
Bombay Victor are tremendous. Are they
in UNESCO side? Not enough. [snorts]
Look, I don't know what you mean by
univilized. Poverty, if you have a state
of poverty in some part of the world,
does it mean that that part of the world
is univilized?
I would say univilized behavior is when
you have no law and order, when people
are doing any kind of nonsense, when you
have violence, when you have
that sort of thing. If you go to Daravi,
you will see no violence. It's pretty
well organized. It has a GDP of more
than a billion per year. It it uh the
people live in peace. They live in an
organized manner. Everybody's employed.
There is no lawlessness. There is no
drunkenness. There is no homelessness in
Daravi. Everyone's employed. Everyone's
gainfully employed. Everyone's doing
some work. People are running
businesses.
I know it can be better. It is
classified as a slum. I suppose it is a
slum. And there are structural issues
within India which is why we still have
these issues over here. So we will
overcome these issues.
No question about that. But
the presence of poverty
is not equivalent to the presence of to
the absence of civilization.
Right? Um the trains and glorious
stations in Bombay. Have you glorious
stations? Have you been to the stations
in what you call Bombay? We call Mumbai
now. Uh there's nothing glorious about
those stations
and all the glory which you see from the
great architecture
that came from Indian money and Indian
labor. Right. So anyway, good to see you
James. Good to see you. Bus says, "Did
the world did the word China come from
Sanskrit word China?" Most likely it
did. Yes. Most likely it came from the
Sanskrit word China. Yeah,
VS says James is always in rebellious
libo bro mode. James does a great job of
bringing bringing out you know issues
and topics that need to be discussed and
I very much appreciate James very much
so. And that brings me to the end of
today's live stream. I have dealt with
all the super chats hopefully.
All right. Okay.
Yeah, I I think I have answered all the
super chat questions and that should do
it. All right. So, thank you so much
everybody. Thank you so much for the
questions. It was great. Once again, I
am not discussing Epstein today. No.
[laughter]
All right. All right. I will do another
live stream tomorrow as you know in
which I will take questions about any
topic. So, ask me all those questions
tomorrow. Thank you so much for the
questions. Keep asking questions. Keep
learning. Keep raising your standards
and I will see you in tomorrow's live
stream. Until then, take care. Good day,
good night, good evening, good morning
wherever you are. I'll see you tomorrow.
Bye-bye.